TRANSITION

John Mudbury was on his way home from the shops, his arms full of Christmas presents. It was after six o’clock and the streets were very crowded. He was an ordinary man, lived in an ordinary suburban flat, with an ordinary wife and four ordinary children. He did not think them ordinary, but everybody else did. He had ordinary presents for each one, a cheap blotter for his wife, a cheap air-gun for the eldest boy, and so forth. He was over fifty, bald, in an office, decent in mind and habits, of uncertain opinions, uncertain politics, and uncertain religion. Yet he considered himself a decided, positive gentleman, quite unaware that the morning newspaper determined his opinions for the day. He just lived—from day to day. Physically, he was fit enough, except for a weak heart (which never troubled him); and his summer holiday was bad golf, while the children bathed and his wife read “Garvice” on the sands. Like the majority of men, he dreamed idly of the past, muddled away the present, and guessed vaguely—after imaginative reading on occasions—at the future.

“I’d like to survive all right,” he said, “provided it’s better than this,” surveying his wife and children, and thinking of his daily toil. “Otherwise——!” and he shrugged his shoulders as a brave man should.

He went to church regularly. But nothing in church convinced him that he did survive, just as nothing in church enticed him into hoping that he would. On the other hand, nothing in life persuaded him that he didn’t, wouldn’t, couldn’t. “I’m an Evolutionist,” he loved to say to thoughtful cronies (over a glass), having never heard that Darwinism had been questioned. ...

And so he came home gaily, happily, with his bunch of Christmas presents “for the wife and little ones,” stroking himself upon their keen enjoyment and excitement. The night before he had taken “the wife” to see Magic at a select London theatre where the Intellectuals went—and had been extraordinarily stirred. He had gone questioningly, yet expecting something out of the common. “It’s not musical,” he warned her, “nor farce, nor comedy, so to speak”; and in answer to her question as to what the Critics had said, he had wriggled, sighed, and put his gaudy necktie straight four times in quick succession. For no “Man in the Street,” with any claim to self-respect, could be expected to understand what the Critics had said, even if he understood the Play. And John had answered truthfully: “Oh, they just said things. But the theatre’s always full—and that’s the only test.”

And just now, as he crossed the crowded Circus to catch his ’bus, it chanced that his mind (having glimpsed an advertisement) was full of this particular Play, or, rather, of the effect it had produced upon him at the time. For it had thrilled him—inexplicably: with its marvellous speculative hint, its big audacity, its alert and spiritual beauty. ... Thought plunged to find something—plunged after this bizarre suggestion of a bigger universe, after this quasi-jocular suggestion that man is not the only—then dashed full-tilt against a sentence that memory thrust beneath his nose: “Science does not exhaust the Universe”—and at the same time dashed full-tilt against destruction of another kind as well ...!

How it happened, he never exactly knew. He saw a Monster glaring at him with eyes of blazing fire. It was horrible! It rushed upon him. He dodged. ... Another Monster met him round the corner. Both came at him simultaneously. ... He dodged again—a leap that might have cleared a hurdle easily, but was too late. Between the pair of them—his heart literally in his gullet—he was mercilessly caught. ... Bones crunched. ... There was a soft sensation, icy cold and hot as fire. Horns and voices roared. Battering-rams he saw, and a carapace of iron. ... Then dazzling light. ... “Always face the traffic!” he remembered with a frantic yell—and, by some extraordinary luck, escaped miraculously on to the opposite pavement. ...

There was no doubt about it. By the skin of his teeth he had dodged a rather ugly death. First ... he felt for his presents—all were safe. And then, instead of congratulating himself and taking breath, he hurried homewards—on foot, which proved that his mind had lost control a bit!—thinking only how disappointed the wife and children would have been if—if anything had happened. ... Another thing he realised, oddly enough, was that he no longer really loved his wife, but had only great affection for her. What made him think of that, Heaven only knows, but he did think of it. He was an honest man without pretence. This came as a discovery somehow. He turned a moment, and saw the crowd gathered about the entangled taxicabs, policemen’s helmets gleaming in the lights of the shop windows ... then hurried on again, his thoughts full of the joy his presents would give ... of the scampering children ... and of his wife—bless her silly heart!—eyeing the mysterious parcels. ...

And, though he never could explain how, he presently stood at the door of the jail-like building that contained his flat, having walked the whole three miles! His thoughts had been so busy and absorbed that he had hardly noticed the length of weary trudge. ... “Besides,” he reflected, thinking of the narrow escape, “I’ve had a nasty shock. It was a d——d near thing, now I come to think of it. ...” He did feel a bit shaky and bewildered. ... Yet, at the same time, he felt extraordinarily jolly and light-hearted. ...

He counted his Christmas parcels ... hugged himself in anticipatory joy ... and let himself in swiftly with his latchkey. “I’m late,” he realised, “but when she sees the brown-paper parcels, she’ll forget to say a word. God bless the old faithful soul.” And he softly used the key a second time and entered his flat on tiptoe. ... In his mind was the master impulse of that afternoon—the pleasure these Christmas presents would give his wife and children. ...

He heard a noise. He hung up hat and coat in the pokey vestibule (they never called it “hall”) and moved softly towards the parlour door, holding the packages behind him. Only of them he thought, not of himself—of his family, that is, not of the packages. Pushing the door cunningly ajar, he peeped in slyly. To his amazement, the room was full of people! He withdrew quickly, wondering what it meant. A party? And without his knowing about it! Extraordinary! ... Keen disappointment came over him. But, as he stepped back, the vestibule, he saw, was full of people too.

He was uncommonly surprised, yet somehow not surprised at all. People were congratulating him. There was a perfect mob of them. Moreover, he knew them all—vaguely remembered them, at least. And they all knew him.

“Isn’t it a game?“ laughed some one, patting him on the back. ”They haven’t the least idea ...!”

And the speaker—it was old John Palmer, the bookkeeper at the office—emphasised the “they.”

“Not the least idea,” he answered with a smile, saying something he didn’t understand, yet knew was right.

His face, apparently, showed the utter bewilderment he felt. The shock of the collision had been greater than he realised evidently. His mind was wandering. ... Possibly! Only the odd thing was—he had never felt so clear-headed in his life. Ten thousand things grew simple suddenly. But, how thickly these people pressed about him, and how—familiarly!

“My parcels,” he said, joyously pushing his way across the throng. “These are Christmas presents I’ve bought for them.” He nodded toward the room. “I’ve saved for weeks—stopped cigars and billiards and—and several other good things—to buy them.”

“Good man!” said Palmer with a happy laugh. “It’s the heart that counts.”

Mudbury looked at him. Palmer had said an amazing truth, only—people would hardly understand and believe him. ... Would they?

“Eh?” he asked, feeling stuffed and stupid, muddled somewhere between two meanings, one of which was gorgeous and the other stupid beyond belief.

“If you please, Mr. Mudbury, step inside. They are expecting you,” said a kindly, pompous voice. And, turning sharply, he met the gentle, foolish eyes of Sir James Epiphany, a director of the Bank where he worked.

The effect of the voice was instantaneous from long habit.

“They are?” he smiled from his heart, and advanced as from the custom of many years. Oh, how happy and gay he felt! His affection for his wife was real. Romance, indeed, had gone, but he needed her—and she needed him. And the children—Milly, Bill, and Jean—he deeply loved them. Life was worth living indeed!

In the room was a crowd, but—an astounding silence. John Mudbury looked round him. He advanced towards his wife, who sat in the corner arm-chair with Milly on her knee. A lot of people talked and moved about. Momentarily the crowd increased. He stood in front of them—in front of Milly and his wife. And he spoke—holding out his packages. “It’s Christmas Eve,” he whispered shyly, “and I’ve—brought you something—something for everybody. Look!” He held the packages before their eyes.

“Of course, of course,” said a voice behind him, “but you may hold them out like that for a century. They’ll never see them!”

“Of course they won’t. But I love to do the old, sweet thing,” replied John Mudbury—then wondered with a gasp of stark amazement why he said it.

“I think——” whispered Milly, staring round her.

“Well, what do you think?” her mother asked sharply. “You’re always thinking something queer.”

“I think,” the child continued dreamily, “that Daddy’s already here.” She paused, then added with a child’s impossible conviction, “I’m sure he is. I feel him.”

There was an extraordinary laugh. Sir James Epiphany laughed. The others—the whole crowd of them—also turned their heads and smiled. But the mother, thrusting the child away from her, rose up suddenly with a violent start. Her face had turned to chalk. She stretched her arms out—into the air before her. She gasped and shivered. There was an awful anguish in her eyes.

“Look!” repeated John, “these are the presents that I brought.”

But his voice apparently was soundless. And, with a spasm of icy pain, he remembered that Palmer and Sir James—some years ago—had died.

“It’s magic,” he cried, “but—I love you, Jinny—I love you—and—and I have always been true to you—as true as steel. We need each other—oh, can’t you see—we go on together—you and I—for ever and ever——”

“Think,” interrupted an exquisitely tender voice, “don’t shout! They can’t hear you—now.” And, turning, John Mudbury met the eyes of Everard Minturn, their President of the year before. Minturn had gone down with the Titanic.

He dropped his parcels then. His heart gave an enormous leap of joy.

He saw her face—the face of his wife—look through him.

But the child gazed straight into his eyes. She saw him.

The next thing he knew was that he heard something tinkling ... far, far away. It sounded miles below him—inside him—he was sounding himself—all utterly bewildering—like a bell. It was a bell.

Milly stooped down and picked the parcels up. Her face shone with happiness and laughter. ...

But a man came in soon after, a man with a ridiculous, solemn face, a pencil, and a notebook. He wore a dark blue helmet. Behind him came a string of other men. They carried something ... something ... he could not see exactly what it was. But when he pressed forward through the laughing throng to gaze upon it, he dimly made out two eyes, a nose, a chin, a deep red smear, and a pair of folded hands upon an overcoat. A woman’s form fell down upon them then, and ... he heard ... soft sounds of children weeping strangely ... and other sounds ... sounds as of familiar voices ... laughing ... laughing gaily.

“They’ll join us presently. It goes like a flash. ...”

And, turning with great happiness in his heart, he saw that Sir James had said it, holding Palmer by the arm as with some natural yet unexpected love of sympathetic friendship.

“Come on,” said Palmer, smiling like a man who accepts a gift in universal fellowship, “let’s help ’em. They’ll never understand. ... Still, we can always try.”

The entire throng moved up with laughter and amusement. It was a moment of hearty, genuine life at last. Delight and Joy and Peace were everywhere.

Then John Mudbury realised the truth—that he was dead.

Traveling Light

A Famous Writer Tells How He Escaped From Possessions

Why own a garden, when half the world is yours to roam over?

Since early childhood it has always been my instinct to “travel light”—not to be choked and worried by possessions. By possessions I mean exactly what I say: a house or apartment, books, pictures, automobile, hors s, property, et cetera, above all, those domestic possessions involved in the term “marriage.” I am fond or children, but I have never wanted children of my own; love may or may not have come to me, but I have never wanted to “own,” (irk owned by, a woman for life.

There, I believe, in that last little phrase, is the key of what I mean—the fundamental principle of this attitude to life that has always been in me: namely, I somehow knew instinctively that he who has possessions is usually owned hr them.

This instinct to reduce life to its simplest terms showed itself in me very young. It was deeper, I think, than the gipsy, vagabond instinct, which made me love to get away by myself, or with one companion to wander off into lonely woods and wild places, to cook my food, make a tire, hear trees rustic in a wind that touched no walls or roofs, to watch the sun set behind a deserted moorland, or see the stars rise over hills where human footsteps never came. This wandering, gips y instinct was strong, but it was not, I think,

the root of thc matter in me. The root of the matter, the fundamental thing in this attitude of mine, was the deep feeling to travel light, to remain unencumbered, to avoid the fuss and entanglements due to owning things, to escape the choking, smothering, suffocating weariness of having a lot of things I did not need. I wanted, no doubt, another boy’s knife or box of matches, but I remember distinctly that I never envied his parents their bigger house than our own, their horses, carriages—above all, their servants and the endless bother of their larger gardens.

And this instinct to do without, to avoid accumulation of unnecessary things, is stronger in me now, at the age of fifty-six, than it was in early boyhood. If I came into ten thousand dollars a year tomorrow, I should not change my mode of life, nor want more than a larger sitting-room, nor wish for a personal servant, nor buy an automobile, nor start a library. I now have a bedroom in London and a bedroom in the country, a dozen books, a trunk of country clothes and a trunk of town clothes. Once or twice a scar I go carefully through what I have accumulated ;things will accumulate somehow!) and sec what I can get rid of. If I had a large income tomorrow, I should do the Same.

The desire to acquire, to possess, is, like hunger and self-preservation, primitive in men. In earliest infancy it declares itself. A baby with a ball craves the ball the other baby plays with, then, having got it, throws it away. Now, let me repeat, by possessions I mean unnecessary possessions—property, properties, things, more than one needs. As a living organism with a body, I find myself stuck fast to the surface of a huge globe that rolls and turns through space. I did not ask to be planted on it; I cannot escape. That body has to be fed, clothed, sheltered. Its needs ate actually not great. There may be, there is, room for inter. [Iteration of the word ••need.s,.. and one body may and does desire more, in terms of food, clothing, shelter, than another.

What was clear to me, even as a Youngster, was that I personally needed very little—the least I could do with. It, further, soon became clear to me that “needs” was a term that could easily become a Djin, a Frankenstein, with an insatiable appetite. With many it often grows into a monster that eats up life itself, so that its victim lives the life of his possessions, nor his own life. Needs Pawl bare to be watched, kept simple, for they grow in like mushromis, and a new “need,” once indulged, soon becomes a habit that seems indispensable to comfort.

“Real living,” says Algernon Blackwood, “is an interior affair. To be owned by possessions is not to live at all.”

This dominating instinct to acquire and possess, then to realize that the thing acquired has little value is the tune we all dance to like frenzied marionettes. A few needs, indeed, are necessary, essential; beyond that point—naturally hard to determine—acquisition is futile childishness. An excess of possessions involves eOrry, anxiety, care and aolturd enpensc. We mend our health and energy, our best years, fghting like cats and dogs to acquire what we do not really want.

In my own case, anyhow, the instinct to keep needs few and simple was certainly natural and inborn. Whence it derived, or why, is a mystery. I was born in a class of English life that had possessions. My mother enjoyed a comfortable jointure on the estate of her first husband, the Duke of Manchester; my father, as Financial Secretary to the Post Office, was well paid. They both had private means of their own as well. My early years were passed in what most would call luxury. Yet, as far back as I can remember, my desire always was to get out of it all, to mope into some kind of life where I could be natural, do without, escape from artificiality, avoid conforming to a standard of needs that we adopted merely because everybody about us also adopted it, to catch my food and cook it over a fire of my own making, to wear “any old thing,” to be free—to know what I called liberty. The desire to possess was not in me.

Life, let me say at once, has very ably seconded this dap instinct in me. Possessions have never come my way—not even within smelling distance. The couple of thousand pounds with which my father sent me out to farm to Canada before I was twenty were lost in six months, since when any such sum of money has carefully avoided me. Life, with tongue in cheek perhaps, noted my attitude to its gifts and consistently encouraged it. Has Ithis been due to the absence of desire, the lack of ambition in me to become a large owner of wordly goods? Perhaps. I cannot say. The fact remains that I have never been tempted yet.

They tell me that with sudden wealth a shutter, so to peak, flies up in the mind, revealing a larger horizon of desires. Things that were not needed before and never men thought about, because they were utterly impossible, become first desirable, then necessary. The individual Changes out of all knowing. This may be true, and I have certainly seen it happen with others. A bachelor friend of mine, with tastes and outlook similar to my own, married a few years ago a woman with a lot of money. As a bachelor he was happy and contented with just enough to live on simply. He was always saying ha had ill he needed and that money would not change him. He sow has five times as much as he had before when he was comfortable in a couple of rooms. He has a car, a town house, a country house, a shooting in Scotland, and he is sot only always “hard up,” but he is discontented, always ‘,tarrying about money, bothered and harassed by posessions he does not really need, but thinks he needs.

In his case that shutter I mentioned flew up to some Pupose; a new horizon of wants, with the power to satisfy them, opened before him. He is changed out of all recognition. Would a similar result, I ask myself, come about in me, too, if the power to accumulate possessions suddenly were mine? I think not.

I have good reasons, too, for thinking not Life, while leasing me, has also tested me. My deep instinct I believe to be sincere and genuine. My rl bachelor friend just menioned, for instance, had never known want in any shape or form; he always had enough money to live in comfort; he had never missed a meal, been obliged to pawn or gone short in the matter of clothes, boots, underwear, laundry. I have known want in every form—want of food, of clothes, of a bed. Pawnbrokers were my intimate friends. Semi-starvation I have experienced for long periods. I have known, over a period of years, what it means to do without necessities, using the word in its strictest sense.

Having lost what cash I had in running a dairy farm in Ontario, Canada, and later a small hotel in Toronto, I drifted, after some months in the backwoods, to New York City. Various hardships followed in due course; I knew life in the raw; I met reality in the face. Nothing tests character better. In such circumstances what is in a man coma out. When, having literally nothing himself and in daily want of necessities, he secs round him people who have everything and to spare he finds out very clearly what it is he dots want. Envy asserts itself. It must. And I remember distinctly that what I envied others was, never their immense possessions, but their liberty. As a reporter, I was always interviewing millionaires, people who owned so much that they hardly knew what to do with it all. Yet their lives, I realized plainly, were not what I craved, for it seemed to me they had lost their liberty. The man I did envy was the man who had enough money for his necessities and, his few wants easily satisfied, knew freedom.

My own dream, in the painful years of hardship between twenty-one and twenty-eight, was to have enough to live on in the woods somewhere—five hundred to seven hundred and fifty dollars a year, I remember, was about my estimate then—so as to be free so develop ideas and concentrate upon theories which lay in me. It was interior, not exterior, ambition that enflamed me. Writing, I saw, was a means by which I might possibly have earned that modest annual income, only I never thought I could write. It crossed my mind vaguely from time to time, but having been rather a failure as a newspaper reporter, it never occurred to me that I could write a story, much less a book. I did not even try. It was much later, at the age of thirty-six, that I began writing suddenly.

During that long period of test (Continued on fade oaf; in New York, at any rate, I know that the desire for possessions, as such, was far from me.

Then Fate played a new card and, after a futile adventure in the Rainy River gold region, posing for a living in artists studios, teaching French and violin to occasional pupils, and a brief experience in making eau de cologne soap, I found myself in better circumstances as Private Sezreca,y to James Speyer, of Speyer Bros. Mr. Speyer was a million ante presumably; he was also a public-spirited philanthropist. My concern with him at the moment, however, is the effect of seeing such riches at close quarters upon myself. Well, smile as many may, it all made me ache. I admired, of course, the fine way he regarded himself evidently as a steward of great wealth, spending it freely to help others. I learned much from his example, should fate ever turn me into an unwilling millionaire. But, simple as his tastes were in a way, the amount of possessions a bachelor needed to feed, clothe and shelter his person, seemed to me fantastic. I kept his personal accounts … I remember I used to sigh for him. What a life! I used to say to myself. And envy, even in its faintest form, did not touch me once.

He was then (1897) building himself a new house in Madison Avenue, a miniture palace of taste, comfort, what some might call splendor, and as it slowly grew and, story by story, became furnished, I used to watch and help,doing my secretary’s work, such as it was, and think to myself: “It’s got you! You’re caught! You’ve lost your liberty!” I envied him to the point of a thousand or two dollars a year, but after that … it seemed to me his possessions called the tune for his dancing. I had no wish to spend my youth accumulating things I could not use and my old age guarding these useless accumulations or paying a lot of hirelings to do so and a second lotof hirelings to watch the first lot of hirelings. People who spent their lives in this fashion, it seemed to me, never lived at all; they were automata without real liberty; their movements, habits, actions dictated by their possessions; owned and driven by what they owned. Real living was an Interior affair, and to spend all one’s energies upon externals was to miss life utterly. The kingdom of heaven—the things worth owning, acquiring—lie within.

It was most assuredly not due to any superior wisdom in me that I realized very early in life that the acquisition of externals meant nothing to me and that all my energies, desires, ambitions turned inwards. ‘Vhat always interested me mos,: was consciousness and its development The proper study of mankind, ‘ said Pope,’ is man”; one single new fact atcut consciousness, about what man essentially is seemed to me of greater value than even a new discovery in science, certainly of more importance than any possible external possession. Knowledge I craved passionately, but it was this, and not that, knowledge. A new discovery in consciousness, I thought, must help the race more than any new discovery in science which adds to its comfort, contributes to its mechanical convenience in speed and communication or increases its mere “power over nature.” The former may improve the man himself; the latter can only better and complicate his physical condition, deepening at the same time his dependence on externals. The man who dnves a machine through the air is not, by so doing, a higher type than he who drives a wooden plow.

Thus, naturally and by temperament, I turned instinctively to the wisdom of the East, where thought and energy are directed to the study and development of consciousness, rather than to the acquisition of externals. Beyond earning a living, there was nothing I wanted from any man, because no man could give me what I wanted. From my point of view, the things that mattered, the nearest to reality we may perhaps get, lay within. I watched the rich; all their energies, I noted, went to increasing what they had, to protecting and guarding it, haunted by terror of loss. With few exceptions, they had no time or inclination to think of anything else. I did not envy them. Possessions involved, I saw, the energies going outward and prevented that inward searching where the things that matter are to be found. I wanted none of those things I would have had to pay others to protect for me by loss and fire policies …

Life has ever seemed to me wonderful, amazing, thrilling. Useless possessions, I have ever felt, must choke, smother and dull this edge of life. Of what use to me is a house with twenty rooms, when I need only two, one to sleep in and one to eat and work in? Of what use a dozen troublesome servants, when I can attend to my own few wants with more success than any personal attendant can? Of what use flower-beds, a copse, a rock-garden, when half the world is free for me to roam over it, with its forests, mountains, acres of free flowers? Of what use a dozen paid hirelings whose interests are not mine, when a little money can buy the simple service that is really necessary?

“Travel light” has always been my motto and always, I think, will be. Remain unencumbered, and you taste the edge of life at its sharpest, its finest, its sweetest.

Two in One

Some idle talker, playing with half-truths, had once told him that he was too self-centred to fall into love‚ÅÝ‚Äîout of himself; he was unwilling to lose himself in another; and that was the reason he had never married. But Le Maitre was not really more of an egoist than is necessary to make a useful man. A too selfless person is ever ineffective. The suggestion, nevertheless, had remained to distress, for he was no great philosopher‚ÅÝ‚Äîmerely a writer of successful tales‚ÅÝ‚Äîtales of wild Nature chiefly; the ‚Äúhuman interest‚Äù (a publisher‚Äôs term) was weak; the great divine enigma of an undeveloped soul‚ÅÝ‚Äîcertainly of a lover‚Äôs or a woman‚Äôs soul‚ÅÝ‚Äîhad never claimed his attention enough, perhaps. He was somewhat too much detached from human life. Nature had laid so powerful a spell upon his heart‚Ää‚Ä¶

‚ÄúI hope she won‚Äôt be late,‚Äù ran the practical thought across his mind as he waited that early Sunday morning in the Great Central Station and reflected that it was the cleanest, brightest, and most airy terminus of all London. He had promised her the whole day out‚ÅÝ‚Äîa promise somewhat long neglected. He was not conscious of doing an unselfish act, yet on the whole, probably, he would rather‚ÅÝ‚Äîor just as soon‚ÅÝ‚Äîhave been alone.

The air was fragrant, and the sunshine blazed in soft white patches on the line. The maddening loveliness of an exceptional spring danced everywhere into his heart. Yes, he rather wished he were going off into the fields and woods alone, instead of with her. Only‚ÅÝ‚Äîshe was really a dear person, more, far more now, than secretary and typist; more, even, than the devoted girl who had nursed him through that illness. A friend she was; the years of their working together had made her that; and she was wise and gentle. Oh, yes; it would be delightful to have her with him. How she would enjoy the long sunny day!

Then he saw her coming towards him through the station. In a patch of sunshine she came, as though the light produced her‚ÅÝ‚Äîcame suddenly from the middle of a group of men in flannels carrying golf-sticks. And he smiled his welcome a little paternally, trying to kill the selfish thought that he would rather have been alone. Soft things fluttered about her. The big hat was becoming. She was dressed in brown, he believed.

He bought a Sunday paper. ‚ÄúI must buy one too,‚Äù she laughed. She chose one with pictures, chose it at random rather. He had never heard its name even. And in a first-class carriage alone‚ÅÝ‚Äîhe meant to do it really well‚ÅÝ‚Äîthey raced through a world of sunshine and brilliant fields to Amersham. She was very happy. She tried every seat in turn; the blazing sheets of yellow‚ÅÝ‚Äîsuch a spring for buttercups there had never been‚ÅÝ‚Äîdrew her from side to side. She put her head out, and nearly lost her big hat, and that soft fluttering thing she wore streamed behind her like the colour of escaping flowers. She opened both windows. The very carriage held the perfume of may that floated over the whole countryside.

He was very nice to her, but read his paper‚ÅÝ‚Äîthough always ready with a smile and answer when she asked for them. She teased and laughed and chattered. The luncheon packages engaged her serious attention. Never for a moment was she still, trying every corner in turn, putting her feet up, and bouncing to enjoy the softness of the first-class cushions. ‚ÄúYou‚Äôll be sitting in the rack next,‚Äù he suggested. But her head was out of the window again and she did not hear him. She was radiant as a child. His paper interested him‚ÅÝ‚Äîbook reviews or something. ‚ÄúI‚Äôve asked you that three times, you know, already,‚Äù he heard her laughing opposite. And with a touch of shame he tossed the paper through the window. ‚ÄúThere! I‚Äôd quite forgotten her again!‚Äù he thought, with a touch of shame. ‚ÄúI must pull myself together.‚Äù For it was true. He had for the moment‚ÅÝ‚Äîmore than once‚ÅÝ‚Äîforgotten her existence, just as though he really were alone.

Together they strolled down through the beech wood towards Amersham, he forever dropping the luncheon packages, which she picked up again and tried to stuff into his pockets. For she refused to carry anything at all. ‚ÄúIt‚Äôs my day out, not yours, remember! I do no work today!‚Äù And he caught her happiness, pausing to watch her while she picked flowers and leaves and all the rest, and disentangling without the least impatience that soft fluttering thing she wore when it caught in thorns, and even talking with her about this wild spring glory as though she were just the companion that he needed out of all the world. He no longer felt quite so conscious of her objective presence as at first. In the train, for instance, he had felt so vividly aware that she was there. Alternately he had forgotten and remembered her presence. Now it was better. They were more together, as it were. ‚ÄúI wish I were alone,‚Äù he thought once more as the beauty of the spring called to him tumultuously and he longed to lie and dream it all, unhampered by another‚Äôs presence. Then, even while thinking it, he realised that he was‚ÅÝ‚Äîalone. It was curious.

This happened even in their first wood when they went downhill into Amersham. As they left it and passed again into the open it came. And on its heels, as he watched her moving here and there, light-footed as a child or nymph, there came this other instinctive thought‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚ÄúI wish I were ten years younger than I am!‚Äù‚ÅÝ‚Äîthe first time in all his life, probably, that such a thought had ever bothered him. Apparently he said it aloud, laughingly, as he watched her dancing movements. For she turned and ran up to his side quickly, her little face quite grave beneath the big hat‚Äôs rim. ‚ÄúYou are!‚Äù That answer struck him as rather wonderful. Who was she after all‚Ää‚Ä¶‚Ää?

And in Amersham they hired from the Griffin a rickety old cart, drawn by a still more rickety horse, to drive them to Penn‚Äôs Woods. She, with her own money, bought stone-bottle ginger-beer‚ÅÝ‚Äîtwo bottles. It made her day complete to have those bottles, though unless they had driven she would have done without them. The street was deserted, drenched in blazing sunshine. Rooks were cawing in the elms behind the church. Not a soul was about as they crawled away from the houses and passed upwards between hedges smothered in cow-parsley over the hill. She had kept her picture-paper. It lay on her lap all the way. She never opened it or turned a single page; but she held it in her lap. They drove in silence. The old man on the box was like a faded, weatherbeaten farmer dressed in somebody else‚Äôs cast-off Sunday coat. He flicked the horse with a tattered whip. Sometimes he grunted. Plover rose from the fields, cuckoos called, butterflies danced sideways past the carriage, eyeing them‚Ää‚Ä¶ and, as they passed through Penn Street, Le Maitre started suddenly and said something. For, again, he had quite forgotten she was there. ‚ÄúWhat a selfish beast I am! Why can‚Äôt I forget myself and my own feelings, and look after her and make her feel amused and happy? It‚Äôs her day out, not mine!‚Äù This, somehow, was the way he put it to himself, just as any ordinary man would have put it. But, when he turned to look at her, he received a shock. Here was something new and unexpected. With a thud it dropped down into his mind‚ÅÝ‚Äîcrash!

For at the sound of his voice she looked up confused and startled into his face. She had forgotten him! For the first time in all the years together, years of work, of semiofficial attention to his least desire, yet of personal devotion as well, because she respected him and thought him wonderful‚ÅÝ‚Äîshe had forgotten he was there. She had forgotten his existence beside her as a separate person. She, too, had been‚ÅÝ‚Äîalone.

It was here, perhaps, he first realised this singular thing that set this day apart from every other day that he had ever known. In reality, of course, it had come far sooner‚ÅÝ‚Äîbegun with the exquisite spring dawn before either of them was awake, had tentatively fluttered about his soul even while he stood waiting for her in the station, come softly nearer all the way in the train, dropped threads of its golden web about him, especially in that first beech wood, then moved with its swifter yet unhurried rush‚ÅÝ‚Äîuntil, here, now, in this startling moment, he realised it fully. Thus steal those changes o‚Äôer the sky, perhaps, that the day itself knows at sunrise, but that unobservant folk do not notice till the sun bursts out with fuller explanation, and they say, ‚ÄúThe weather‚Äôs changed; how delightful! How unexpected!‚Äù Le Maitre had never been very observant‚ÅÝ‚Äîof people.

And then in this deep, lonely valley, too full of sunshine to hold anything else, it seemed, they stopped where the beech woods trooped to the edge of the white road. No wind was here; it was still and silent; the leaves glittered, motionless. They entered the thick trees together, she carrying the ginger-beer bottles and that picture-paper. He noticed that: the way she held it, almost clutched it, still unopened. Her face, he saw, was pale. Or was it merely the contrast of the shade? The trees were very big and wonderful. No birds sang, the network of dazzling sunshine-patches in the gloom bewildered a little.

At first they did not talk at all, and then in hushed voices. But it was only when they were some way into the wood, and she had put down the bottles‚ÅÝ‚Äîthough not the paper‚ÅÝ‚Äîto pick a flower or spray of leaves, that he traced the singular secret thrill to its source and understood why he had felt‚ÅÝ‚Äîno, not uneasy, but so strangely moved. For he had asked the sleepy driver of the way, and how they might best reach Beaconsfield across these Penn Woods, and the old man‚Äôs mumbled answer took no note of‚ÅÝ‚Äîher:

‚ÄúIt‚Äôs a bit rough, maybe, on t‚Äôother side, stony like and steep, but that ain‚Äôt nothing for a gentleman‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhen he‚Äôs alone‚Ää‚Ä¶‚Ää!‚Äù

The words disturbed him with a sense of darkness, yet of wonder. As though the old man had not noticed her; almost as though he had seen only one person‚ÅÝ‚Äîhimself.

They lunched among heather and bracken just beside a pool of sunshine. In front lay a copse of pines, with little beeches in between. The roof was thick just there, the stillness haunting. All the countryside, it seemed, this Sunday noon, had gone to sleep, he and she alone left out of the deep, soft dream. He watched those pines, mothering the slim young beeches, the brilliant fresh green of whose lower branches, he thought, were like little platforms of level sunlight amid the general gloom‚ÅÝ‚Äîpatches that had left the ground to escape by the upper air and had then been caught.

‚ÄúLook,‚Äù he heard, ‚Äúthey make one think of laughter crept in unawares among a lot of solemn monks‚ÅÝ‚Äîor of children lost among grave elder beings whose ways are dull and sombre!‚Äù It was his own thought continued‚Ää‚Ä¶ yet it was she, lying there beside him, who had said it‚Ää‚Ä¶

And all that wonderful afternoon she had this curious way of picking the thoughts out of his mind and putting them into words for him. ‚ÄúLook,‚Äù she said again later, ‚Äúyou can always tell whether the wind loves a tree or not by the way it blows the branches. If it loves them, it tries to draw them out to go away with it. The others it merely shakes carelessly as it passes!‚Äù It was the very thought in his own mind, too. Indeed, he had been on the point of saying it, but had desisted, feeling she would not understand‚ÅÝ‚Äîwith the half wish‚ÅÝ‚Äîthough far less strong than before‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat he were alone to enjoy it all in his own indulgent way. Then, even more swiftly, came that other strange sensation that he was alone all the time; more‚ÅÝ‚Äîthat he was for the first time in his life most wonderfully complete and happy, all sense of isolation gone.

He turned quickly the instant she had said it. But not quickly enough. By the look in her great grey eyes, by the expression on the face where the discarded hat no longer hid it, he read the same amazing enigma he had half divined before. She, too, was‚ÅÝ‚Äîalone. She had forgotten him again‚ÅÝ‚Äîforgotten his presence‚ÅÝ‚Äîradiant and happy without him, enjoying herself in her own way. She had merely uttered her delightful thought aloud, as if speaking to herself!

How the afternoon, with its long sunny hours, passed so quickly away, he never understood, nor how they made their way eventually to Beaconsfield through other woods and over other meadows. He remembers only that the whole time he kept forgetting that she was with him, and then suddenly remembering it again. And once on the grass, when they rested to drink the cold tea from his rather musty flask, he lit his pipe, and after a bit he‚ÅÝ‚Äîdozed. He actually slept; for ten minutes at her side, yes, he slept. He heard her laughing at him, but the laughter was faint and very far away; it might just as well have been the wind in the cow-parsley that said, ‚ÄúIf you sleep, I shall change you‚ÅÝ‚Äîchange you while you sleep!‚Äù And for some minutes after he woke again, it hardly seemed queer to him that he did not see her, for when he noticed her coming towards him from the hedgerow, her arms full of flowers and things, he only thought, ‚ÄúOh, there she is‚Äù‚ÅÝ‚Äîas though her absence, or his own absence in sleep, were not quite the common absences of the world.

And he remembered that on the walk to the village her shoe hurt her, and he offered to carry her, and that then she took her shoe off and ran along the grass beside the lane the whole way. But it was at the inn where they had their supper that the oddest thing of all occurred, for the deaf and rather stupid servant girl would insist on laying the table on the lawn for‚ÅÝ‚Äîone.

‚ÄúOh, expectin‚Äô someone, are yer?‚Äù she said at last. ‚ÄúIs that it?‚Äù and so brought plates and knives for two. The girl never once looked at his companion‚ÅÝ‚Äîalmost as though she did not see her and seemed unaware of her presence. Le Maitre began to feel that he was dreaming. This was a dream-country, where the people had curious sight. He remembered the driver‚Ää‚Ä¶

In the dusk they made their way to the station. They spoke no word. He kept losing sight of her. Once or twice he forgot who he was. But the whole amazing thing blazed into him most strongly, showing how it had seized upon his mind, when he stood before the ticket-window and hesitated‚ÅÝ‚Äîfor a second‚ÅÝ‚Äîhow many tickets he should buy. He stammered at length for two first-class, but he was absurdly flustered for a second. It had actually occurred to him that they needed only one ticket‚Ää‚Ä¶

And suddenly in the train he understood‚ÅÝ‚Äîand his heart came up in his throat. They were alone. He turned to her where she lay in the corner, feet up, weary, crumpled among the leaves and flowers she had gathered. Like a hedgerow flower she looked, tired by the sunshine and the wind. In one hand was the picture-paper, still unopened and unread, symbol of everyday reality. She was dozing certainly, if not actually asleep. So he woke her with a touch, calling her name aloud.

There were no words at first. He looked at her, coming up very close to do so, and she looked back at him‚ÅÝ‚Äîstraight into his eyes‚ÅÝ‚Äîjust as she did at home when they were working and he was explaining something important. And then her own eyes dropped, and a deep blush spread over all her face.

‚ÄúI wasn‚Äôt asleep‚ÅÝ‚Äîreally,‚Äù she said, as he took her at last into his arms; ‚ÄúI was wondering‚ÅÝ‚Äîwhen‚ÅÝ‚Äîyou‚Äôd find out‚ÅÝ‚Äî‚Äù

‚ÄúCome to myself, you mean?‚Äù he asked tremblingly.

‚ÄúWell,‚Äù she hesitated, as soon as she got breath, ‚Äúthat I am yourself‚ÅÝ‚Äîand that you are me. Of course, we‚Äôre really only one. I knew it years‚ÅÝ‚Äîoh, years and years ago‚Ää‚Ä¶‚Äù

Up and Down

His vagueness, apparently, is only on the surface of his mind; down at the centre the pulses of life throb with unusual vigour and decision. And I think the explanation of his puzzled expression and dazed manner—to say nothing of his idiotic replies—when addressed upon ordinary topics is due to the fact that he prefers to live in that hot and very active centre. He dislikes being called out of it.

Down there his creative imagination is forever at work: he sees clearly, thinks hard, acts even splendidly. But the moment you speak to him about trivial things the mists gather about his eyes, his voice hesitates, his hands make futile gestures, and he screws up his face into an expression of puzzled alarm. Up he comes to the best of his ability, but it is clear he is vexed at being disturbed.

“Oh yes, I think so—very, he replied the other day as we met on our way to the Club and I asked if he had enjoyed his! holiday.

“Awful amount of rain, though, wasn’t there?”

“Was there, now? Yes, there must have been, of course. It was a wet summer.”

He looked at me as though I were a comparative stranger, although our intimacy is of years’ standing, and our talks on life, literature, and all the rest are a chief pleasure to each of us. We had not met for some months. I wanted to pierce through to that hot centre where the real man lived, and to find out what the real man had been doing during the interval. He came up but slowly, however.

“You went to the mountains as usual, I suppose?” he asked, with his mind obviously elsewhere. He hopped hopped along the pavement with his quick, birdlike motion.

“Mountains, yes. And you?

He made no reply. From his face I could tell he had come about halfway up, but was already on the way down again. Once he got back to that centre of his I should get nothing out of him at all.

“And you?” I repeated louder. Abroad, I suppose, somewhere?”

” Well-er-not exactly,” he” mumbled.” That is to say-1-er-went to Switzerland somewhere-Austria, I mean-down there on the way towards Italy beyond Bozen, you know.” He ended the sentence very loud indeed, with quite absurd emphasis, as his way is when he knows he hasn’t been listening. “I found a quiet inn out of the tourist track and did a rare lot of work there too.” His face cleared and the brown eyes began to glow a little. It was like seeing the sun through opening mists. Come in, and I’ll tell you about it,” he added, in an eager whisper, as we reached the Club doors.

At the same moment, however, the porter came down the steps and touched his hat, and my vague friend, recognising a face he felt he ought to know, stopped to ask him how he was, and whether So-and-so was back yet; and while the porter replied briefly and respectfully I saw to my dismay the mists settle down again upon the other’s face. A moment later the porter touched his hat again and moved off down the street. My friend looked round at me as though I had but just arrived upon the scene.

Here we are,” he observed gently,” at the Club. I think I shall go in. What are you going to do?”

“I’m coming in too,” I said.

“Good,” he murmured;” let’s go in together, then,” his thoughts working away busily at something deep within him.

On our way to the hat-racks, and all up the winding stairs, he mumbled away about the wet summer, and tourists, and his little mountain inn, but never a word of the work I was so anxious to hear about, and he so anxious really to tell. In the reading-room I manoeuvred to get two armchairs side by side before he could seize the heap of papers he smothered his lap with, but never read.

“And where have you been all the summer?”? he asked, crossing his little legs and speaking in a voice loud enough to have been heard in the street.” Somewhere in the mountains, I suppose, as usual?”

“You were going to tell me about the work you got through up in your lonely inn,” I insisted sharply. “Was it a play, or a novel, or criticism, or what?” He looked so small and lost in the big armchair that I felt quite ashamed of myself for speaking so violently. He turned round on the slippery leather and offered me a cigarette. The glow came back to his face.

“Well,” he said, as a matter of fact it was both. That is, I was preparing a stage version of my new novel.” All the mist had gone now; he was alive at the centre, and thoroughly awake. He snapped his case to and put it away before I had taken my cigarette. But, of course, he did not notice that, and held out a lighted match to my lips as though there was something there to light.

“No, thanks,” I said quickly, fearful that if I asked again for the cigarette the mists would instantly gather once more and the real man disappear.

” Won’t you really, though?” he said, blowing the match out and forgetting to light his own cigarette at the same time. “I did the whole scenario, and most of the first act. There was nothing else to do. It rained all the time, and the place was quiet as the grave

A waiter brought him several letters on a tray. He took them automatically. The face clouded a bit.

“What’ll you have?” he asked absentmindedly, acting automatically upon the presence of the waiter.

“Nothing, thanks.”

Nor will I, then. Oh yes, I will, thoughI’ll have some dry ginger ale. Here, waiter! Bring me a small dry ginger ale.”

The waiter, with the force of habit, bent his head questioningly for my order too.

You said—?” asked my exasperating friend. He was right down in the mists now, and I knew I should never get him up again this side of lunch.

“I said nothing, thanks.”

“Nothing, then, for this gentleman,” he continued, gazing up at the waiter as though he were some monster seen for the first time,” and for me—a dry ginger ale, please.”

“Yes, sir,” said the man, moving off.

“Small,” the other called after him.

” Yessir-small.’

“And a slice of lemon in it.” The waiter inclined his head respectfully from the door. The other turned to me, searching in his perturbed mind—I could tell it by the way his eyes worked for the trail of his vanished conversation. Before he got it, however, he slithered round again on the leather seat towards the door.

“A bit of ice too, don’t forget!”

The waiter’s head peeped round the corner, and from the movement of his lips I gathered he repeated the remark about the bit of ice.

“I did say ‘dry’?”my friend asked, looking anxiously at me ;” didn’t I?”

” You did.”

“And a bit of lemon?”

“And a slice of lemon.”

“And what are you going to have, then? Upon my word, old man, I forgot to ask you.” He looked so distressed that it was impossible to show impatience.

“Nothing, thanks. You asked me, you know.”

A pause fell between us. I gave it up. He would talk when he wanted to, but there was no forcing him. It struck me suddenly that he had a rather fagged and weary look for a man who had been spending several weeks at a mountain inn with work he loved. The pity and affection his presence always wakes in me ran a neck-and-neck race. At that “centre” of his, I knew full well, he was ever devising plans for the helping of others, quite as much as creating those remarkable things that issued periodically, illunderstood by a sensation-loving public, from the press. A sharp telepathic suspicion flashed through my mind, but before there was time to give it expression in words, up came the waiter with a long glass of ginger ale fizzing on a tray.

He has it to my vague friend, and my vague friend took it and handed it to me.

“But it’s yours, my dear chap,” I suggested.

He looked puzzled for a second, and then his face cleared. “I forget what you ordered,” he observed softly, looking interrogatively at the waiter and at me. We informed him simultaneously, “Nothing,” and the waiter respectfully mentioned the price of the drink. My friend’s left hand plunged into his trousers pocket, while his right carried the glass to his lips. Perhaps his left hand did not know what his right was about, or perhaps his mind was too far away to direct the motions of either with safety. Anyhow, the result was deplorable. He swallowed an uncomfortable gulp of airbubbles and ginger-and choked-over me, over the waiter and tray, over his beard and clothes. The floating lump of ice bobbed up and hit his. I never saw a man look so surprised and distressed in my life. I took the glass from him, and when his left hand finally emerged with money he handed it first vaguely to me as though I were the waiter-for which there was no real excuse, since we were not in evening dress.

When, at length, order was restored and he was sipping quietly at the remains of the fizzing liquid, he looked up at me over the brim of his glass and remarked, with more concentration on the actual present than he had yet shown:

By the way, you know, I’m going away tomorrow-going abroad for my holiday. Taking a lot of work with me, too

“But you’ve only just come back I” I expostulated, with a feeling very like anger in my heart.

He shook his head with decision. Evidently that choking had choked him into the living present. He was really up” this time, and not likely to go down again.

“No, no,” he replied ;” I’ve been here all the summer in town looking after old Podger

“Old Podger!” I remembered a dirty, downat-heel old man I once met at my friend’s rooms, a poet who had”smothered his splendid talent” in drink, and who was always at starvation’s door. What in the world was the matter with Podger?”

“D.T. I’ve been nursing him through it. The poor devil nearly went under this time. I’ve got him into a home down in the country at last, but all August he was-well, we thought he was gone.”

All August! So that was how my friend’s summer had been spent. With never a word of thanks probably at that!

“But your mountain inn beyond Bozen! You said”

“Did I? I must be woolgathering,” he , laughed, with that beautifully tender smile that comes sometimes to his delicate, dreamy face. “That was last year. I spent my holidays last year up there. How stupid of me to get so absurdly muddled!” He plunged his nose into I the empty glass, waiting for the last drop to trickle out, with his neck at an angle that betrayed the collar to be undone and the tie sadly frayed at the edges.

“But all the work you said you did up there -the scenario and the first act and-and He turned upon me with such sudden energy that I fairly jumped. Then, in a voice that mumbled the first half of his sentence, but shouted the end like a German officer giving instructions involving life or death, I heard :

“But, my dear good fellow, you don’t half listen to what I say! All that work, as I told you just now, is what I expect and mean to do when I get up there. Now—have you got it clear at last?”

He looked me up and down with great energy. By biting the inner side of my lip I kept my face grave. Later we went down to lunch together, and I heard details of the weeks of unselfish devotion he had lavished upon” old Podger.” I would give a great deal to possess some of the driving power for good that throbs and thrills at the real centre of my old friend with the vague manner and the absentminded surface. But he is a singular contradiction, and almost always misunderstood. I should like to know, too, what Podger thinks.

Value

In Life and Death, Changed Views

There sas a funeral yesterday in this lonely little village of the Jura. and the world to-day looks somehow differ- ent. HiuMan beings instinctively trans- fer their emotions to inanimate Na- ture, obtaining in this way relief. This endless sighing of deep woods ex- Presses more than our little throats and breasts can compass. This streaming rain pours grief from all the hills with a wholesale grandeur that makes our tiny tears seem futile. Yea, the world looks different here to-day, and, to tell the truth. we all feel ashamed to notice it. None of us sap anything. Some try boldly to conceal it even, but all are silent. for the lonely old English lady who has left ws we unanimously voted a bore while we had her. and probably there igs not one of us who has net said plainly to hik neighbor “It is really time she went: she’s a perfect plague.”

But now that she has taken us at eur word there is this strange differ- ence in sky and forest and mountain. The English clergyman came out from fhe neighboring town to bury her, tall, striding, athletic figure ef a man who walks but never takes the train, and the peasants asked one another, ‘Mais quest-ce quil fait, ce Paeteur anglais, avec sa rele de ouit sur le bras?” having never seen a surplice before, nor a muscular Christian who carried his robes of office so openly.

For five years, in and out, we have known her wasted figure and high querulous voice at the Pension de la Poste, where we took our dejeuner and souper. We have known her oft-told stories every one, and heard them, summer. spring, winter; witnessed her incessant fault-finding. marvelled at her strenuous vitality for well past seventy, disliked, while secretly ap- proving, her untiring efforts to in- troduce sweet old-fashioned manners duto a heterogeneous collection of bour- geois foreigners, German, Swiss, Rus- sian, Armenian, Persian, and Italian; and been worried out of our lives by ber consistent high-mindedness in and out of season. preached unflinchingly and sting.ngly whether the moment Was rpe tor itor not.

She was of Quaker stock, a thin, wiry, teasing little old lady, fearlessly out- spoken, with a fiery temper, a dusty black dress, keen blue eves that looked amazingly youthful in the deeply-lined face, and jeer old hands that were knotted with rheumatism. Yet in life we should net have said “poor old hangs: the description would have been more harsh Alert as a cricket and quick as a hawk, she would dart about the Pension on her self-imposed mission like a lean grey cat, pouncing upon of. fenders before they knew she was in- the room. If an armchair racked up the carpet, its occupant, old or young, was forced to rise while she put it straight. if the boys came into the lit- the salon with their muddy boots on, dirtying the furniture, she would have them upstairs, grumbling ut obedient, im a twinkling: and if the girls we el- ders romped with sometimes sat unbe- comingly on the sofa, she would dart. across the room to pull their little skirts two inches nearer to their shoes, er alter their attitude, with the firm re- mark that “when I was a girl, young ladies did not cross their legs in the drawing-room.” These were the little tiresome things she did. but she carried her high, strict standard into the gen- eral conduct of life as well, and though ber interference was exasperating—pa- rents resenting it for their children as being a reflection upon themselves—it was invariably right. There was the pinch, we all felt criticised. She was upright as a character in a Sunday school book no, slackness in her any- where. tier standard became the standard «of the entire Pension—when Rhe vas present and, new thot she has: gone, the Pension realises that secretly io was rather proud of her. Even in the Kitchen.’ Which of us can ever forget the stern: that followed her discovery of the cook breaking a doubtful egg in- to our supper omelette … her know- ledge of French being confined = to “nong pas, “mercy,” and “e’est hon- teux”—pronounced “ongtoo?” She bad the right of entree into the kitchen af- ter that. We all profited!

Her memory was sadly failing when she arrived five years ago with her three black tin boxes, but within an- other year or so it had finally disap- peared. And the contrast was singular between this indication of great age and the active energy she had of genuine youth. Within fifteen minutes of being introduced to some new ar- rival, she would ask in her courteous wuy, ‘Please, who are those people? Would you kindly introduce me?” yet she would dance with us in the corridor when someone played a waltz, and even join in pillow-fighis, while pulling down skirts and making sure that the ser- vant was clearing the supper-table properly. she would walk four miles imo tuwn to pay a boot bill, forgotten for many months, and when she reach- ed the shop would wonder why she had come there, and order another pair of boots instead. I do believe my me- mory inust be failing,’ was her invari- able explanation of every similar con- fusion. adding proudly, ‘How old do you think Iam? Don’t guess toe lw. i dont mind!” People guessed = ac- «ording to their balance between tact and interest, but the answer was al- ways the same: “I was born the year Queen Victoria came to the throne!” And the other, Armenian, Russian, Ger- man, or English, had to make the cal- culation, or else feel foolish. Imme- diately then, if her listener betrayed a sign of sympathy, the stories would ap- pear: there were eight or ten of them, each leading neatly into the other, and hardly a day passed without someone receiving the entire collection full in the face. Escape, once they began, was impossible. The first was usually about the brother whose beard was so long that he tied it round his neck when Playing cricket; and the last was to do with the superiority of Cornish over Devonshire cream. In between were two others, about the Cornish woman who talked with Queen Victoria, the the Cornish man who had seen a fairy. Her acuteness of hearing was uncanny. “The faintest mention at the table of “Cornish Cream,” “Fairy,” or “Beard” tickled the memory cell and produced the story. If teasing is a sign of lov- fing then the children loved her well! The old lady had not the slightest idea that she had told the stories before—perhaps at the beginning of the very meal that witnessed their repetition. Out they poured, and with much convic- tion, dignity, and personal interest in the telling, that her end of the table was compelled to listen or provoke a «rushing criticism of its manners, “Devonshire Cream is the best,” would @ay one of the English children in a pause, whispering it probably; and in- stantly the keen old face would lighten up, eyes grown alert, and manner im- Perieus. “There’s no such thing; there’s only Cornish Cream. The Phoeni- cians brought the method first § inte Cornwall when they came for tin—.” “Venetians?” a child always asked gravely. “No, Phoenicians, I said; Fou don’t iisten properly, dear.” “They brought their tins with them?” would be asked at once. “No,” with perfect good temper, “J said they came te get tin from the Cornish mines, and intro- duced the method of making the cream at the same time. And the real way of making it is this ⸺*“ while the entire table listened to the bitter end. It ‘was a recognised game to s@¢ how many times in a single mea! the simies could be produced; and the elders did not in- rerfere, because the old lady obviously enjoyed the telling so enormously, pro- vided her suspicions were not aroused. Personally, Urough 1 heard the stories daily for mamy months, I never saw them aroused: her patience and good ‘temper were inexhaustible. They were ‘an expression of her standard. She in- variably won the day.

And the stories she read lasted ag long as the ones she told, for in the several years of our acquaintance I never saw her with a new book. A paper-covered novel, grey with use, sup- plied all her reading, because she began the book every day afresh, for- getting that she had already finished it. It was pathetic to see her in the even- ings, two cats inextricably mingled on her small, sloping lap, while she turned the opening pages of this everlasting volume, and wondered audibly who it was had “fingered it and turned the leaves down” when she wasn’t looking. She must have read that novel a hun- dred times, yet each day she came to it with original, fresh interest. Some- times she fell asleep: the book would slip to the ground; someone would mention her name; she would wake with a start, glance sharply round the room, miss her novel, pick it up, and—begin again at the first page. Ques- tioned about it, she would say, “It begins wéll: I think I shall like it.” It was the same with everything. That consecutive thinking which is memory was no longer possible, Yet in other ways the stream of life ran so forcibly in her. She painted pretty water- colors, and was energetic with her lace. “I’ll show you one of my pictures,” she would say, and fly up the steep stairs two steps at a time to her tiny room on the top floor—to come down again with some lace, or her book, or perhaps to forget why she had made the jour- ney at ull, and not to reappear again. More than once, on these occasions, she undressed and got into bed. “Now, tell me, when dees Christmas fall this vear?” she asked me once the very day after the festivities, and it was no uncommon thing to have a week com- posed entirely of Sundays. There was one story, however, she never repeated, She told it once in a fit of confidence, and the Irishwoman who heard it passed it.on tou me. It is eloquent of the splendid pluck which was her out- standing characteristic, of that gener- ous, high courage, rather, which was the foundation of her “standard.” For she lived still with her old love story of fifty years ago, her pain, her great sacrifice—yet without a hint of bitter- ness or regret. A clergyman, well on the way to preferment in his calling, loved her and asked her to be his wife. She loved him in return. But first she consulted a next-of-kin, who was mar- ried and had many children, the man whe would naturally inherit from her. And this next-of-kin explained to her bluntly that his children might suffer if she married. “I don’t regret it,” she said to the Irishwoman. “The man I loved is dead nuw, and | should be a widow.” An orphan, and without brothers or sisters, she went lonely through her long life, ending it here in this little village pension in the Jura, where we teased, admired, re- spected, and avoided her. … Her in- come was £60 @ year!

We were in the Alps when the news came that she was sinking. We get back too late. Everybody came to inquire’ it was astonishing how many friends she had made among the vigne- rons and local shop folk. “On ne touche pas,” went out the word from the mis- tress of the Pension, a kindly woman, who had borne with her all these years with infinite sympathy and patience. For the custom in this village after a death is to come and shake hands for- mally with the relatives, or those who pass for such. “On touche” is their way of describi the little function. But in a case like this, where there are no blood relations, the formality is dis- pensed with. “On ne touche pas”—and the little old lady has gone to her crave in the village cemetery among the larches, more respected than when she lived among us, and certainly more loved. She had value. We miss her keenly. Her high standard will live after her, for a time at least, and she has not lived in vain. The world looks different to-day.

Violence

“But what seems so odd to me, so horribly pathetic, is that such people don’t resist,” said Leidall, suddenly entering the conversation. The intensity of his tone startled everybody; it was so passionate, yet with a beseeching touch that made the women feel uncomfortable a little. “As a rule, I’m told, they submit willingly, almost as though—”

He hesitated, grew confused, and dropped his glance to the floor; and a smartly-dressed woman, eager to be heard, seized the opening. “Oh, come now,” she laughed; “one always hears of a man being put into a strait waistcoat. I’m sure he doesn’t slip it on as if he were going to a dance!” And she looked flippantly at Leidall, whose casual manners she resented. “People are put under restraint. It’s not in human nature to accept it—healthy human nature, that is?” But for some reason no one took her question up. “That is so, I believe, yes,” a polite voice murmured, while the group at tea in the Dover Street Club turned with one accord to Leidall as to one whose interesting sentence still remained unfinished. He had hardly spoken before, and a silent man is ever credited with wisdom.

“As though—you were just saying, Mr. Leidall?” a quiet little man in a dark corner helped him.

“As though, I meant, a man in that condition of mind is not insane all through,” Leidall continued stammeringly; “but that some wise portion of him watches the proceeding with gratitude, and welcomes the protection against himself. It seems awfully pathetic. Still”—again hesitating and fumbling in his speech—“er—it seems queer to me that he should yield quietly to enforced restraint—the waistcoat, handcuffs, and the rest.” He looked round hurriedly, half suspiciously, at the faces in the circle, then dropped his eyes again to the floor. He sighed, leaning back in his chair. “I cannot understand it,” he added, as no one spoke, but in a very low voice, and almost to himself. “One would expect them to struggle furiously.”

Someone had mentioned that remarkable book, The Mind that Found Itself, and the conversation had slipped into this serious vein. The women did not like it. What kept it alive was the fact that the silent Leidall, with his handsome, melancholy face, had suddenly wakened into speech, and that the little man opposite to him, half invisible in his dark corner, was assistant to one of London’s great hypnotic doctors, who could, an he would, tell interesting and terrible things. No one cared to ask the direct question, but all hoped for revelations, possibly about people they actually knew. It was a very ordinary tea-party indeed. And this little man now spoke, though hardly in the desired vein. He addressed his remarks to Leidall across the disappointed lady.

“I think, probably, your explanation is the true one,” he said gently, “for madness in its commoner forms is merely want of proportion; the mind gets out of right and proper relations with its environment. The majority of madmen are mad on one thing only, while the rest of them is as sane as myself—or you.”

The words fell into the silence. Leidall bowed his agreement, saying no actual word. The ladies fidgeted. Someone made a jocular remark to the effect that most of the world was mad anyhow, and the conversation shifted with relief into a lighter vein—the scandal in the family of a politician. Everybody talked at once. Cigarettes were lit. The corner soon became excited and even uproarious. The tea-party was a great success, and the offended lady, no longer ignored, led all the skirmishes—towards herself. She was in her element. Only Leidall and the little invisible man in the corner took small part in it; and presently, seizing the opportunity when some new arrivals joined the group, Leidall rose to say his adieux, and slipped away, his departure scarcely noticed. Dr. Hancock followed him a minute later. The two men met in the hall; Leidall already had his hat and coat on. “I’m going West, Mr. Leidall. If that’s your way too, and you feel inclined for the walk, we might go together.” Leidall turned with a start. His glance took in the other with avidity—a keenly-searching, hungry glance. He hesitated for an imperceptible moment, then made a movement towards him, half inviting, while a curious shadow dropped across his face and vanished. It was both pathetic and terrible. The lips trembled. He seemed to say, “God bless you; do come with me!” But no words were audible.

“It’s a pleasant evening for a walk,” added Dr. Hancock gently; “clean and dry under foot for a change. I’ll get my hat and join you in a second.” And there was a hint, the merest flavour, of authority in his voice.

That touch of authority was his mistake. Instantly Leidall’s hesitation passed. “I’m sorry,” he said abruptly, “but I’m afraid I must take a taxi. I have an appointment at the Club, and I’m late already.” “Oh, I see,” the other replied, with a kindly smile; “then I mustn’t keep you. But if you ever have a free evening, won’t you look me up, or come and dine? You’ll find my telephone number in the book. I should like to talk with you about—those things we mentioned at tea.” Leidall thanked him politely and went out. The memory of the little man’s kindly sympathy and understanding eyes went with him.

“Who was that man?” someone asked, the moment Leidall had left the tea-table. “Surely he’s not the Leidall who wrote that awful book some years ago?”

“Yes—the Gulf of Darkness. Did you read it?”

They discussed it and its author for five minutes, deciding by a large majority that it was the book of a madman. Silent, rude men like that always had a screw loose somewhere, they agreed. Silence was invariably morbid.

“And did you notice Dr. Hancock? He never took his eyes off him. That’s why he followed him out like that. I wonder if he thought anything!”

“I know Hancock well,” said the lady of the wounded vanity. “I’ll ask him and find out.” They chattered on, somebody mentioned a risqué play, the talk switched into other fields, and in due course the tea-party came to an end.

And Leidall, meanwhile, made his way towards the Park on foot, for he had not taken a taxi after all. The suggestion of the other man, perhaps, had worked upon him. He was very open to suggestion. With hands deep in his overcoat pockets, and head sunk forward between his shoulders, he walked briskly, entering the Park at one of the smaller gates. He made his way across the wet turf, avoiding the paths and people. The February sky was shining in the west; beautiful clouds floated over the houses; they looked like the shoreline of some radiant strand his childhood once had known. He sighed; thought dived and searched within; self-analysis, that old, implacable demon, lifted its voice; introspection took the reins again as usual. There seemed a strain upon the mind he could not dispel. Thought circled poignantly. He knew it was unhealthy, morbid, a sign of those many years of difficulty and stress that had marked him so deeply, but for the life of him he could not escape from the hideous spell that held him. The same old thoughts bored their way into his mind like burning wires, tracing the same unanswerable questions. From this torture, waking or sleeping, there was no escape. Had a companion been with him it might have been different. If, for instance, Dr. Hancock—

He was angry with himself for having refused—furious; it was that vile, false pride his long loneliness had fostered. The man was sympathetic to him, friendly, marvellously understanding; he could have talked freely with him, and found relief. His intuition had picked out the little doctor as a man in ten thousand. Why had he so curtly declined his gentle invitation? Dr. Hancock knew; he guessed his awful secret. But how? In what had he betrayed himself?

The weary self-questioning began again, till he sighed and groaned from sheer exhaustion. He must find people, companionship, someone to talk to. The Club—it crossed his tortured mind for a second—was impossible; there was a conspiracy among the members against him. He had left his usual haunts everywhere for the same reason—his restaurants where he had his lonely meals; his music-hall, where he tried sometimes to forget himself; his favourite walks, where the very policeman knew and eyed him. And, coming to the bridge across the Serpentine just then, he paused and leaned over the edge, watching a bubble rise to the surface.

“I suppose there are fish in the Serpentine?” he said to a man a few feet away.

They talked a moment—the other was evidently a clerk on his way home, and then the stranger edged off and continued his walk, looking back once or twice at the sad-faced man who had addressed him. “It’s ridiculous, that with all our science we can’t live under water as the fish do,” reflected Leidall, and moved on round the other bank of the water, where he watched a flight of duck whirl down from the darkening air and settle with a long, mournful splash beside the bushy island. “Or that, for all our pride of mechanism in a mechanical age, we cannot really fly.” But these attempts to escape from self were never very successful. Another part of him looked on and mocked. He returned ever to the endless introspection of self-analysis, and in the deepest moment of it—ran into a big, motionless figure that blocked his way. It was the Park policeman, the one who had always eyed him. He sheered off suddenly towards the trees, while the man, recognising him, touched his cap respectfully. “It’s a pleasant evening, sir; turned quite mild again.” Leidall mumbled some reply or other, and hurried on to hide himself among the shadows of the trees. The policeman stood and watched him, till the darkness swallowed him. “He knows too!” groaned the wretched man. And every bench was occupied; every face turned to watch him; there were even figures behind the trees. He dared not go into the street, for the very taxi-drivers were against him. If he gave an address, he would not be driven to it; the man would know, and take him elsewhere. And something in his heart, sick with anguish, weary with the endless battle, suddenly yielded.

“There are fish in the Serpentine,” he remembered the stranger had said. “And,” he added to himself, with a wave of delicious comfort, “they lead secret, hidden lives that no one can disturb.” His mind cleared surprisingly. In the water he could find peace and rest and healing. Good Lord! How easy it all was! Yet he had never thought of it before. He turned sharply to retrace his steps, but in that very second the clouds descended upon his thought again, his mind darkened, he hesitated. Could he get out again when he had had enough? Would he rise to the surface? A battle began over these questions. He ran quickly, then stood still again to think the matter out. Darkness shrouded him. He heard the wind rush laughing through the trees. The picture of the whirring duck flashed back a moment, and he decided that the best way was by air, and not by water. He would fly into the place of rest, not sink or merely float; and he remembered the view from his bedroom window, high over old smoky London town, with a drop of eighty feet onto the pavements. Yes, that was the best way. He waited a moment, trying to think it all out clearly, but one moment the fish had it, and the next the birds. It was really impossible to decide. Was there no one who could help him, no one in all this enormous town who was sufficiently on his side to advise him on the point? Some clearheaded, experienced, kindly man?

And the face of Dr. Hancock flashed before his vision. He saw the gentle eyes and sympathetic smile, remembered the soothing voice and the offer of companionship he had refused. Of course, there was one serious drawback: Hancock knew. But he was far too tactful, too sweet and good a man to let that influence his judgment, or to betray in any way at all that he did know.

Leidall found it in him to decide. Facing the entire hostile world, he hailed a taxi from the nearest gate upon the street, looked up the address in a chemist’s telephone book, and reached the door in a condition of delight and relief. Yes, Dr. Hancock was at home. Leidall sent his name in. A few minutes later the two men were chatting pleasantly together, almost like old friends, so keen was the little man’s intuitive sympathy and tact. Only Hancock, patient listener though he proved to be, was uncommonly full of words. Leidall explained the matter very clearly. “Now, what is your decision, Dr. Hancock? Is it to be the way of the fish or the way of the duck?” And, while Hancock began his answer with slow, well-chosen words, a new idea, better than either, leaped with a flash into his listener’s mind. It was an inspiration. For where could he find a better hiding-place from all his troubles than Hancock himself? The man was kindly; he surely would not object. Leidall this time would not hesitate a second. He was tall and broad; Hancock was small; yet he was sure there would be room. He sprang upon him like a wild animal. He felt the warm, thin throat yield and bend between his great hands … then darkness, peace and rest, a nothingness that surely was the oblivion he had so long prayed for. He had accomplished his desire. He had secreted himself forever from persecution—inside the kindliest little man he had ever met—inside Hancock. …

He opened his eyes and looked about him into a room he did not know. The walls were soft and dimly coloured. It was very silent. Cushions were everywhere. Peaceful it was, and out of the world. Overhead was a skylight, and one window, opposite the door, was heavily barred. Delicious! No one could get in. He was sitting in a deep and comfortable chair. He felt rested and happy. There was a click, and he saw a tiny window in the door drop down, as though worked by a sliding panel. Then the door opened noiselessly, and in came a little man with smiling face and soft brown eyes—Dr. Hancock.

Leidall’s first feeling was amazement. “Then I didn’t get into him properly after all! Or I’ve slipped out again, perhaps! The dear, good fellow!” And he rose to greet him. He put his hand out, and found that the other came with it in some inexplicable fashion. Movement was cramped. “Ah, then I’ve had a stroke,” he thought, as Hancock pressed him, ever so gently, back into the big chair. “Do not get up,” he said soothingly but with authority; “sit where you are and rest. You must take it very easy for a bit; like all clever men who have overworked—”

“I’ll get in the moment he turns,” thought Leidall. “I did it badly before. It must be through the back of his head, of course, where the spine runs up into the brain,” and he waited till Hancock should turn. But Hancock never turned. He kept his face towards him all the time, while he chatted, moving gradually nearer to the door. On Leidall’s face was the smile of an innocent child, but there lay a hideous cunning behind that smile, and the eyes were terrible.

“Are those bars firm and strong,” asked Leidall, “so that no one can get in?” He pointed craftily, and the doctor, caught for a second unawares, turned his head. That instant Leidall was upon him with a roar, then sank back powerless into the chair, unable to move his arms more than a few inches in any direction. Hancock stepped up quietly and made him comfortable again with cushions.

And something in Leidall’s soul turned round and looked another way. His mind became clear as daylight for a moment. The effort perhaps had caused the sudden change from darkness to great light. A memory rushed over him. “Good God!” he cried. “I am violent. I was going to do you an injury—you who are so sweet and good to me!” He trembled dreadfully, and burst into tears. “For the sake of Heaven,” he implored, looking up, ashamed and keenly penitent, “put me under restraint. Fasten my hands before I try it again.” He held both hands out willingly, beseechingly, then looked down, following the direction of the other’s kind brown eyes. His wrists, he saw, already wore steel handcuffs, and a strait waistcoat was across his chest and arms and shoulders.

Wayfarers

I missed the train at Evian, and, after infinite trouble, discovered a motor that would take me, ice-axe and all, to Geneva. By hurrying, the connection might be just possible. I telegraphed to Haddon to meet me at the station, and lay back comfortably, dreaming of the precipices of Haute Savoie. We made good time; the roads were excellent, traffic of the slightest, when—crash! There was an instant’s excruciating pain, the sun went out like a snuffed candle, and I fell into something as soft as a bed of flowers and as yielding to my weight as warm water. …

It was very warm. There was a perfume of flowers. My eyes opened, focused vividly upon a detailed picture for a moment, then closed again. There was no context—at least, none that I could recall—for the scene, though familiar as home, brought nothing that I definitely remembered. Broken away from any sequence, unattached to any past, unaware even of my own identity, I simply saw this picture as a camera snaps it off from the world, a scene apart, with meaning only for those who knew the context:

The warm, soft thing I lay in was a bed—big, deep, comfortable; and the perfume came from flowers that stood beside it on a little table. It was in a stately, ancient chamber, with lofty ceiling and immense open fireplace of stone; old-fashioned pictures—familiar portraits and engravings I knew intimately—hung upon the walls; the floor was bare, with dignified, carved furniture of oak and mahogany, huge chairs and massive cupboards. And there were latticed windows set within deep embrasures of grey stone, where clambering roses patterned the sunshine that cast their moving shadows on the polished boards. With the perfume of the flowers there mingled, too, that delicate, elusive odour of age—of wood, of musty tapestries in spacious halls and corridors, and of chambers long unopened to the sun and air.

By the door that stood ajar far away at the end of the room—very far away it seemed—an old lady, wearing a little cap of silk embroidery, was whispering to a man of stern, uncompromising figure, who, as he listened, bent down to her with a grave and even solemn face. A wide stone corridor was just visible through the crack of the open door behind her.

The picture flashed, and vanished. The numerous details I took in because they were well known to me already. That I could not supply the context was merely a trick of the mind, the kind of trick that dreams play. Darkness swamped vision again. I sank back into the warm, soft, comfortable bed of delicious oblivion. There was not the slightest desire to know; sleep and soft forgetfulness were all I craved.

But a little later—or was it a very great deal later?—when I opened my eyes again, there was a thin trail of memory. I remembered my name and age. I remembered vaguely, as though from some unpleasant dream, that I was on the way to meet a climbing friend in the Alps of Haute Savoie, and that there was need to hurry and be very active. Something had gone wrong, it seemed. There had been a stupid, violent disaster, pain in it somewhere, an accident. Where were my belongings? Where, for instance, was my precious ice-axe—tried old instrument on which my life and safety depended? A rush of jumbled questions poured across my mind. The effort to sort them hurt atrociously. …

A figure stood beside my bed. It was the same old lady I had seen a moment ago—or was it a month ago, even last year perhaps? And this time she was alone. Yet, though familiar to me as my own right hand, I could not for the life of me attract her name. Searching for it brought the pain again. Instead, I asked an easier question; it seemed the most important somehow, though a feeling of shame came with it, as though I knew I was talking nonsense:

“My ice-axe—is it safe? It should have stood any ordinary strain. It’s ash. …” My voice failed absurdly, caught away by a whisper halfway down my throat. What was I talking about? There was vile confusion somewhere.

She smiled tenderly, sweetly, as she placed her small, cool hand upon my forehead. Her touch calmed me as it always did, and the pain retreated a little.

“All your things are safe,” she answered, in a voice so soft beneath the distant ceiling it was like a bird’s note singing in the sky. “And you are also safe. There is no danger now. The bullet has been taken out and all is going well. Only you must be patient, and lie very still, and rest.” And then she added the morsel of delicious comfort she knew quite well I waited for: “Marion is near you all day long, and most of the night besides. She rarely leaves you. She is in and out all day.”

I stared, thirsting for more. Memory put certain pieces in their place again. I heard them click together as they joined. But they only tried to join. There were several pieces missing. They must have been lost in the disaster. The pattern was too ridiculous.

“I ought to tel—telegraph—” I began, seizing at a fragment that poked its end up, then plunged out of sight again before I could read more of it. The pieces fell apart; they would not hold together without these missing fragments. Anger flamed up in me.

“They’re badly made,” I said, with a petulance I was secretly ashamed of; “you have chosen the wrong pieces! I’m not a child—to be treated—” A shock of heat tore through me, led by a point of iron, with blasting pain.

“Sleep, my poor dear Félix, sleep,” she murmured soothingly, while her tiny hand stroked my forehead, just in time to prevent that pointed, hot thing entering my heart. “Sleep again now, and a little later you shall tell me their names, and I will send on horseback quickly—”

“Telegraph—” I tried to say, but the word went lost before I could pronounce it. It was a nonsense word, caught up from dreams. Thought fluttered and went out.

“I will send,” she whispered, “in the quickest possible way. You shall explain to Marion. Sleep first a little longer; promise me to lie quite still and sleep. When you wake again, she will come to you at once.”

She sat down gently on the edge of the enormous bed, so that I saw her outline against the window where the roses clambered to come in. She bent over me—or was it a rose that bent in the wind across the stone embrasure? I saw her clear blue eyes—or was it two raindrops upon a withered rose-leaf that mirrored the summer sky?

“Thank you,” my voice murmured with intense relief, as everything sank away and the old-world garden seemed to enter by the latticed windows. For there was a power in her way that made obedience sweet, and her little hand, besides, cushioned the attack of that cruel iron point so that I hardly felt its entrance. Before the fierce heat could reach me, darkness again put out the world. …

Then, after a prodigious interval, my eyes once more opened to the stately, old-world chamber that I knew so well; and this time I found myself alone. In my brain was a stinging, splitting sensation, as though Memory shook her pieces together with angry violence, pieces, moreover, made of clashing metal. A degrading nausea almost vanquished me. Against my feet was a heated metal body, too heavy for me to move, and bandages were tight round my neck and the back of my head. Dimly, it came back to me that hands had been about me hours ago, soft, ministering hands that I loved. Their perfume lingered still. Faces and names fled in swift procession past me, yet without my making any attempt to bid them stay. I asked myself no questions. Effort of any sort was utterly beyond me. I lay and watched and waited, helpless and strangely weak.

One or two things alone were clear. They came, too, without the effort to think them:

There had been a disaster; they had carried me into the nearest house; and—the mountain heights, so keenly longed for, were suddenly denied me. I was being cared for by kind people somewhere far from the world’s high routes. They were familiar people, yet for the moment I had lost the name. But it was the bitterness of losing my holiday climbing that chiefly savaged me, so that strong desire returned upon itself unfulfilled. And, knowing the danger of frustrated yearnings, and the curious states of mind they may engender, my tumbling brain registered a decision automatically:

“Keep careful watch upon yourself,” it whispered.

For I saw the peaks that towered above the world, and felt the wind rise from the hidden valleys. The perfume of lonely ridges came to me, and I saw the snow against the blue-black sky. Yet I could not reach them. I lay, instead, broken and useless upon my back, in a soft, deep, comfortable bed. And I loathed the thought. A dull and evil fury rose within me. Where was Haddon? He would get me out of it if anyone could. And where was my dear, old trusted ice-axe? Above all, who were these gentle, old-world people who cared for me? … And, with this last thought, came some fairy touch of sweetness so delicious that I was conscious of sudden resignation—more, even of delight and joy.

This joy and anger ran races for possession of my mind, and I knew not which to follow: both seemed real, and both seemed true. The cruel confusion was an added torture. Two sets of places and people seemed to mingle.

“Keep a careful watch upon yourself,” repeated the automatic caution.

Then, with returning, blissful darkness, came another thing—a tiny point of wonder, where light entered in. I thought of a woman. … It was a vehement, commanding thought; and though at first it was very close and real—as much of Today as Haddon and my precious ice-axe—the next second it was leagues away in another world somewhere. Yet, before the confusion twisted it all askew, I knew her; I remembered clearly even where she lived; that I knew her husband, too—had stayed with them in—in Scotland—yes, in Scotland. Yet no word in this life had ever crossed my lips, for she was not free to come. Neither of us, with eyes or lips or gesture, had ever betrayed a hint to the other of our deeply hidden secret. And, although for me she was the woman, my great yearning—long, long ago it was, in early youth—had been sternly put aside and buried with all the vigour nature gave me. Her husband was my friend as well.

Only, now, the shock had somehow strained the prison bars, and the yearning escaped for a moment full-fledged, and vehement with passion long denied. The inhibition was destroyed. The knowledge swept deliciously upon me that we had the right to be together, because we always were together. I had the right to ask for her.

My mind was certainly a mere field of confused, ungoverned images. No thinking was possible, for it hurt too vilely. But this one memory stood out with violence. I distinctly remember that I called to her to come, and that she had the right to come because my need was so peremptory. To the one most loved of all this life had brought me, yet to whom I had never spoken because she was in another’s keeping, I called for help, and called, I verily believe, aloud:

“Please come!” Then, close upon its heels, the automatic warning again: “Keep close watch upon yourself … !”

It was as though one great yearning had loosed the other that was even greater, and had set it free.

Disappearing consciousness then followed the cry for an incalculable distance. Down into subterraneans within myself that were positively frightening it plunged away. But the cry was real; the yearning appeal held authority in it as of command. Love gave the right, supplied the power as well. For it seemed to me a tiny answer came, but from so far away that it was scarcely audible. And names were nowhere in it, either in answer or appeal.

“I am always here. I have never, never left you!”

The unconsciousness that followed was not complete, apparently. There was a memory of effort in it, of struggle, and, as it were, of searching. Someone was trying to get at me. I tossed in a troubled sea upon a piece of wreckage that another swimmer also fought to reach. Huge waves of transparent green now brought this figure nearer, now concealed it, but it came steadily on, holding out a rope. My exhaustion was too great for me to respond, yet this swimmer swept up nearer, brought by enormous rollers that threatened to engulf us both. The rope was for my safety, too. I saw hands outstretched. In the deep water I saw the outline of the body, and once I even saw the face. But for a second, merely. The wave that bore it crashed with a horrible roar that smothered us both and swept me from my piece of wreckage. In the violent flood of water the rope whipped against my feeble hands. I grasped it. A sense of divine security at once came over me—an intolerable sweetness of utter bliss and comfort, then blackness and suffocation as of the grave. The white-hot point of iron struck me. It beat audibly against my heart. I heard the knocking. The pain brought me up to the surface, and the knocking of my dreams was in reality a knocking on the door. Someone was gently tapping.

Such was the confusion of images in my pain-racked mind, that I expected to see the old lady enter, bringing ropes and ice-axes, and followed by Haddon, my mountaineering friend; for I thought that I had fallen down a deep crevasse and had waited hours for help in the cold, blue darkness of the ice. I was too weak to answer, and the knocking for that matter was not repeated. I did not even hear the opening of the door, so softly did she move into the room. I only knew that before I actually saw her, this wave of intolerable sweetness drenched me once again with bliss and peace and comfort, my pain retreated, and I closed my eyes, knowing I should feel that cool and soothing hand upon my forehead.

The same minute I did feel it. There was a perfume of old gardens in the air. I opened my eyes to look the gratitude I could not utter, and saw, close against me—not the old lady, but the young and lovely face my worship had long made familiar. With lips that smiled their yearning and eyes of brown that held tears of sympathy, she sat down beside me on the bed. The warmth and fragrance of her atmosphere enveloped me. I sank away into a garden where spring melts magically into summer. Her arms were round my neck. Her face dropped down, so that I felt her hair upon my cheek and eyes. And then, whispering my name twice over, she kissed me on the lips.

“Marion,” I murmured.

“Hush! Mother sends you this,” she answered softly. “You are to take it all; she made it with her own hands. But I bring it to you. You must be quite obedient, please.”

She tried to rise, but I held her against my breast.

“Kiss me again and I’ll promise obedience always,” I strove to say. But my voice refused so long a sentence, and anyhow her lips were on my own before I could have finished it. Slowly, very carefully, she disentangled herself, and my arms sank back upon the coverlet. I sighed in happiness. A moment longer she stood beside my bed, gazing down with love and deep anxiety into my face.

“And when all is eaten, all, mind, all,” she smiled, “you are to sleep until the doctor comes this afternoon. You are much better. Soon you shall get up. Only, remember,” shaking her finger with a sweet pretence of looking stern, “I shall exact complete obedience. You must yield your will utterly to mine. You are in my heart, and my heart must be kept very warm and happy.”

Her eyes were tender as her mother’s, and I loved the authority and strength that were so real in her. I remembered how it was this strength that had sealed the contract her beauty first drew up for me to sign. She bent down once more to arrange my pillows.

“What happened to—to the motor?” I asked hesitatingly, for my thoughts would not regulate themselves. The mind presented such incongruous fragments.

“The—what?” she asked, evidently puzzled. The word seemed strange to her. “What is that?” she repeated, anxiety in her eyes.

I made an effort to tell her, but I could not. Explanation was suddenly impossible. The whole idea dived away out of sight. It utterly evaded me. I had again invented a word that was without meaning. I was talking nonsense. In its place my dream came up. I tried to tell her how I had dreamed of climbing dangerous heights with a stranger, and had spoken another language with him than my own—English, was it?—at any rate, not my native French.

“Darling,” she whispered close into my ear, “the bad dreams will not come back. You are safe here, quite safe.” She put her little hand like a flower on my forehead and drew it softly down the cheek. “Your wound is already healing. They took the bullet out four days ago. I have got it,” she added with a touch of shy embarrassment, and kissed me tenderly upon my eyes.

“How long have you been away from me?” I asked, feeling exhaustion coming back.

“Never once for more than ten minutes,” was the reply. “I watched with you all night. Only this morning, while mother took my place, I slept a little. But, hush!” she said, with dear authority again; “you are not to talk so much. You must eat what I have brought, then sleep again. You must rest and sleep. Goodbye, goodbye, my love. I shall come back in an hour, and I shall always be within reach of your dear voice.”

Her tall, slim figure, dressed in the grey I loved, crossed silently to the door. She gave me one more look—there was all the tenderness of passionate love in it—and then was gone.

I followed instructions meekly, and when a delicious sleep stole over me soon afterwards, I had forgotten utterly the ugly dream that I was climbing dangerous heights with another man, forgotten as well everything else, except that it seemed so many days since my love had come to me, and that my bullet wound would after all be healed in time for our wedding on the day so long, so eagerly waited for.

And when, several hours later, her mother came in with the doctor—his face less grave and solemn this time—the news that I might get up next day and lie a little in the garden, did more to heal me than a thousand bandages or twice that quantity of medical instructions.

I watched them as they stood a moment by the open door. They went out very slowly together, speaking in whispers. But the only thing I caught was the mother’s voice, talking brokenly of the great wars. Napoleon, the doctor was saying in a low, hushed tone, was in full retreat from Moscow, though the news had only just come through. They passed into the corridor then, and there was a sound of weeping as the old lady murmured something about her son and the cruelty of Heaven. “Both will be taken from me,” she was sobbing softly, while he stooped to comfort her; “one in marriage, and the other in death.” They closed the door then, and I heard no more.

I

Convalescence seemed to follow very quickly then, for I was utterly obedient as I had promised, and never spoke of what could excite me to my own detriment—the wars and my own unfortunate part in them. We talked instead of our love, our already too-long engagement, and of the sweet dream of happiness that life held waiting for us in the future. And, indeed, I was sufficiently weary of the world to prefer repose to much activity, for my body was almost incessantly in pain, and this old garden where we lay between high walls of stone, aloof from the busy world and very peaceful, was far more to my taste just then than wars and fighting.

The orchards were in blossom, and the winds of spring showered their rain of petals upon the long, new grass. We lay, half in sunshine, half in shade, beneath the poplars that lined the avenue towards the lake, and behind us rose the ancient grey stone towers where the jackdaws nested in the ivy and the pigeons cooed and fluttered from the woods beyond.

There was loveliness everywhere, but there was sadness too, for though we both knew that the wars had taken her brother whence there is no return, and that only her aged, failing mother’s life stood between ourselves and the stately property, there hid a sadness yet deeper than either of these thoughts in both our hearts. And it was, I think, the sadness that comes with spring. For spring, with her lavish, short-lived promises of eternal beauty, is ever a symbol of passing human happiness, incomplete and always unfulfilled. Promises made on earth are playthings, after all, for children. Even while we make them so solemnly, we seem to know they are not meant to hold. They are made, as spring is made, with a glory of soft, radiant blossoms that pass away before there is time to realise them. And yet they come again with the return of spring, as unashamed and glorious as if Time had utterly forgotten.

And this sadness was in her too. I mean it was part of her and she was part of it. Not that our love could change to pass or die, but that its sweet, so-long-desired accomplishment must hold away, and, like the spring, must melt and vanish before it had been fully known. I did not speak of it. I well understood that the depression of a broken body can influence the spirit with its poisonous melancholy, but it must have betrayed itself in my words and gestures, even in my manner too. At any rate, she was aware of it. I think, if truth be told, she felt it too. It seemed so painfully inevitable.

My recovery, meanwhile, was rapid, and from spending an hour or two in the garden, I soon came to spend the entire day. For the spring came on with a rush, and the warmth increased deliciously. While the cuckoos called to one another in the great beech-woods behind the château, we sat and talked and sometimes had our simple meals or coffee there together, and I particularly recall the occasion when solid food was first permitted me and she gave me a delicate young bondelle, fresh caught that very morning in the lake. There were leaves of sweet, crisp lettuce with it, and she picked the bones out for me with her own white hands.

The day was radiant, with a sky of cloudless blue, soft airs stirred the poplar crests; the little waves fell on the pebbly beach not fifty metres away, and the orchard floor was carpeted with flowers that seemed to have caught from heaven’s stars the patterns of their yellow blossoms. The bees droned peacefully among the fruit trees; the air was full of musical deep hummings. My former vigour stirred delightfully in my blood, and I knew no pain, beyond occasional dull twinges in the head that came with a rush of temporary darkness over my mind. The scar was healed, however, and the hair had grown over it again. This temporary darkness alarmed her more than it alarmed me. There were grave complications, apparently, that I did not know of.

But the deep-lying sadness in me seemed independent of the glorious weather, due to causes so intangible, so far off that I never could dispel them by arguing them away. For I could not discover what they actually were. There was a vague, distressing sense of restlessness that I ought to have been elsewhere and otherwise, that we were together for a few days only, and that these few days I had snatched unlawfully from stern, imperative duties. These duties were immediate, but neglected. In a sense I had no right to this springtide of bliss her presence brought me. I was playing truant somehow, somewhere. It was not my absence from the regiment; that I know. It was infinitely deeper, set to some enormous scale that vaguely frightened me, while it deepened the sweetness of the stolen joy.

Like a child, I sought to pin the sunny hours against the sky and make them stay. They passed with such a mocking swiftness, snatched momentarily from some big oblivion. The twilights swallowed our days together before they had been properly tasted, and on looking back, each afternoon of happiness seemed to have been a mere moment in a flying dream. And I must have somehow betrayed the aching mood, for Marion turned of a sudden and gazed into my face with yearning and anxiety in the sweet brown eyes.

“What is it, dearest?” I asked, “and why do your eyes bring questions?”

“You sighed,” she answered, smiling a little sadly; “and sighed so deeply. You are in pain again. The darkness, perhaps, is over you?” And her hand stole out to meet my own. “You are in pain?”

“Not physical pain,” I said, “and not the darkness either. I see you clearly,” and would have told her more, as I carried her soft fingers to my lips, had I not divined from the expression in her eyes that she read my heart and knew all my strange, mysterious forebodings in herself.

“I know,” she whispered before I could find speech, “for I feel it too. It is the shadow of separation that oppresses you—yet of no common, measurable separation you can understand. Is it not that?”

Leaning over then, I took her close into my arms, since words in that moment were mere foolishness. I held her so that she could not get away; but even while I did so it was like trying to hold the spring, or fasten the flying hour with a fierce desire. All slipped from me, and my arms caught at the sunshine and the wind.

“We have both felt it all these weeks,” she said bravely, as soon as I had released her, “and we both have struggled to conceal it. But now—” she hesitated for a second, and with so exquisite a tenderness that I would have caught her to me again but for my anxiety to hear her further words—“now that you are well, we may speak plainly to each other, and so lessen our pain by sharing it.” And then she added, still more softly: “You feel there is ‘something’ that shall take you from me—yet what it is you cannot discover nor divine. Tell me, Félix—all your thought, that I in turn may tell you mine.”

Her voice floated about me in the sunny air. I stared at her, striving to focus the dear face more clearly for my sight. A shower of apple blossoms fell about us, and her words seemed floating past me like those passing petals of white. They drifted away. I followed them with difficulty and confusion. With the wind, I fancied, a veil of indefinable change slipped across her face and eyes.

“Yet nothing that could alter feeling,” I answered; for she had expressed my own thought completely. “Nor anything that either of us can control. Only—perhaps, that everything must fade and pass away, just as this glory of the spring must fade and pass away—”

“Yet leaving its sweetness in us,” she caught me up passionately, “and to come again, my beloved, to come again in every subsequent life, each time with an added sweetness in it too!” Her little face showed suddenly the courage of a lion in its eyes. Her heart was ever braver than my own, a vigorous, fighting soul. She spoke of lives, I prattled of days and hours merely.

A touch of shame stole over me. But that delicate, swift change in her spread too. With a thrill of ominous warning I noticed how it rose and grew about her. From within, outwards, it seemed to pass—like a shadow of great blue distance. Shadow was somewhere in it, so that she dimmed a little before my very eyes. The dreadful yearning searched and shook me, for I could not understand it, try as I would. She seemed going from me—drifting like her words and like the apple blossoms.

“But when we shall no longer be here to know it,” I made answer quickly, yet as calmly as I could, “and when we shall have passed to some other place—to other conditions—where we shall not recognise the joy and wonder. When barriers of mist shall have rolled between us—our love and passion so made-over that we shall not know each other”—the words rushed out feverishly, half beyond control—“and perhaps shall not even dare to speak to each other of our deep desire—”

I broke off abruptly, conscious that I was speaking out of some unfamiliar place where I floundered, helpless among strange conditions. I was saying things I hardly understood myself. Her bigger, deeper mood spoke through me, perhaps.

Her darling face came back again; she moved close within reach once more.

“Hush, hush!” she whispered, terror and love both battling in her eyes. “It is the truth, perhaps, but you must not say such things. To speak them brings them closer. A chain is about our hearts, a chain of fashioning lives without number, but do not seek to draw upon it with anxiety or fear. To do so can only cause the pain of wrong entanglement, and interrupt the natural running of the iron links.” And she placed her hand swiftly upon my mouth, as though divining that the bleak attack of anguish was again upon me with its throbbing rush of darkness.

But for once I was disobedient and resisted. The physical pain, I realised vividly, was linked closely with this spiritual torture. One caused the other somehow. The disordered brain received, though brokenly, some hints of darker and unusual knowledge. It had stammered forth in me, but through her it flowed easily and clear. I saw the change move more swiftly then across her face. Some ancient look passed into both her eyes.

And it was inevitable; I must speak out, regardless of mere bodily well-being.

“We shall have to face them some day,” I cried, although the effort hurt abominably, “then why not now?” And I drew her hand down and kissed it passionately over and over again. “We are not children, to hide our faces among shadows and pretend we are invisible. At least we have the Present—the Moment that is here and now. We stand side by side in the heart of this deep spring day. This sunshine and these flowers, this wind across the lake, this sky of blue and this singing of the birds—all, all are ours now. Let us use the moment that Time gives, and so strengthen the chain you speak of that shall bring us again together times without number. We shall then, perhaps, remember. Oh, my heart, think what that would mean—to remember!”

Exhaustion caught me, and I sank back among my cushions. But Marion rose up suddenly and stood beside me. And as she did so, another Sky dropped softly down upon us both, and I smelt again the incense of old, old gardens that brought long-forgotten perfumes, incredibly sweet, but with it an ache of far-off, passionate remembrance that was pain. This great ache of distance swept over me like a wave.

I know not what grand change then was wrought upon her beauty, so that I saw her defiant and erect, commanding Fate because she understood it. She towered over me, but it was her soul that towered. The rush of internal darkness in me blotted out all else. The familiar, present sky grew dim, the sunshine faded, the lake and flowers and poplars dipped away. Conditions a thousand times more vivid took their place. She stood out, clear and shining in the glory of an undressed soul, brave and confident with an eternal love that separation strengthened but could never, never change. The deep sadness I abruptly realised, was very little removed from joy—because, somehow, it was the condition of joy. I could not explain it more than that.

And her voice, when she spoke, was firm with a note of steel in it; intense, yet devoid of the wasting anger that passion brings. She was determined beyond Death itself, upon a foundation sure and lasting as the stars. The heart in her was calm, because she knew. She was magnificent.

“We are together—always,” she said, her voice rich with the knowledge of some unfathomable experience, “for separation is temporary merely, forging new links in the ancient chain of lives that binds our hearts eternally together.” She looked like one who has conquered the adversity Time brings, by accepting it. “You speak of the Present as though our souls were already fitted now to bid it stay, needing no further fashioning. Looking only to the Future, you forget our ample Past that has made us what we are. Yet our Past is here and now, beside us at this very moment. Into the hollow cups of weeks and months, of years and centuries, Time pours its flood beneath our eyes. Time is our schoolroom. … Are you so soon afraid? Does not separation achieve that which companionship never could accomplish? And how shall we dare eternity together if we cannot be strong in separation first?”

I listened while a flood of memories broke up through film upon film and layer upon layer that had long covered them.

“This Present that we seem to hold between our hands,” she went on in that earnest, distant voice, “is our moment of sweet remembrance that you speak of, of renewal, perhaps, too, of reconciliation—a fleeting instant when we may kiss again and say goodbye, but with strengthened hope and courage revived. But we may not stay together finally—we cannot—until long discipline and pain shall have perfected sympathy and schooled our love by searching, difficult tests, that it may last forever.”

I stretched my arms out dumbly to take her in. Her face shone down upon me, bathed in an older, fiercer sunlight. The change in her seemed in an instant then complete. Some big, soft wind blew both of us ten thousand miles away. The centuries gathered us back together.

“Look, rather, to the Past,” she whispered grandly, “where first we knew the sweet opening of our love. Remember, if you can, how the pain and separation have made it so worth while to continue. And be braver thence.”

She turned her eyes more fully upon my own, so that their light persuaded me utterly away with her. An immense new happiness broke over me. I listened, and with the stirrings of an ampler courage. It seemed I followed her down an interminable vista of remembrance till I was happy with her among the flowers and fields of our earliest preexistence.

Her voice came to me with the singing of birds and the hum of summer insects.

“Have you so soon forgotten,” she sighed, “when we knew together the perfume of the hanging Babylonian Gardens, or when the Hesperides were so soft to us in the dawn of the world? And do you not remember,” with a little rise of passion in her voice, “the sweet plantations of Chaldea, and how we tasted the odour of many a drooping flower in the gardens of Alcinous and Adonis, when the bees of olden time picked out the honey for our eating? It is the fragrance of those first hours we knew together that still lies in our hearts today, sweetening our love to this apparent suddenness. Hence comes the full, deep happiness we gather so easily Today. … The breast of every ancient forest is torn with storms and lightning … that’s why it is so soft and full of little gardens. You have forgotten too easily the glades of Lebanon, where we whispered our earliest secrets while the big winds drove their chariots down those earlier skies. …”

There rose an indescribable tempest of remembrance in my heart as I strove to bring the pictures into focus; but words failed me, and the hand I eagerly stretched out to touch her own, met only sunshine and the rain of apple blossoms.

“The myrrh and frankincense,” she continued in a sighing voice that seemed to come with the wind from invisible caverns in the sky, “the grapes and pomegranates—have they all passed from you, with the train of apes and peacocks, the tigers and the ibis, and the hordes of dark-faced slaves? And this little sun that plays so lightly here upon our woods of beech and pine—does it bring back nothing of the old-time scorching when the olive slopes, the figs and ripening cornfields heard our vows and watched our love mature? … Our spread encampment in the Desert—do not these sands upon our little beach revive its lonely majesty for you, and have you forgotten the gleaming towers of Semiramis … or, in Sardis, those strange lilies that first tempted our souls to their divine disclosure … ?”

Conscious of a violent struggle between pain and joy, both too deep for me to understand, I rose to seize her in my arms. But the effort dimmed the flying pictures. The wind that bore her voice down the stupendous vista fled back into the caverns whence it came. And the pain caught me in a vice of agony so searching that I could not move a muscle. My tongue lay dry against my lips. I could not frame a word of any sentence. …

Her voice presently came back to me, but fainter, like a whisper from the stars. The light dimmed everywhere; I saw no more the vivid, shining scenery she had summoned. A mournful dusk instead crept down upon the world she had momentarily revived.

“… we may not stay together,” I heard her little whisper, “until long discipline shall have perfected sympathy, and schooled our love to last. For this love of ours is forever, and the pain that tries it is the furnace that fashions precious stones. …”

Again I stretched my arms out. Her face shone a moment longer in that forgotten fiercer sunlight, then faded very swiftly. The change, like a veil, passed over it. From the place of prodigious distance where she had been, she swept down towards me with such dizzy speed. As she was Today I saw her again, more and more.

“Pain and separation, then, are welcome,” I tried to stammer, “and we will desire them”—but my thought got no further into expression than the first two words. Aching blotted out coherent utterance.

She bent down very close against my face. Her fragrance was about my lips. But her voice ran off like a faint thrill of music, far, far away. I caught the final words, dying away as wind dies in high branches of a wood. And they reached me this time through the droning of bees and of waves that murmured close at hand upon the shore.

“… for our love is of the soul, and our souls are moulded in Eternity. It is not yet, it is not now, our perfect consummation. Nor shall our next time of meeting know it. We shall not even speak. … For I shall not be free. …” was what I heard. She paused.

“You mean we shall not know each other?” I cried, in an anguish of spirit that mastered the lesser physical pain.

I barely caught her answer:

“My discipline then will be in another’s keeping—yet only that I may come back to you … more perfect … in the end. …”

The bees and waves then cushioned her whisper with their humming. The trail of a deeper silence led them far away. The rush of temporary darkness passed and lifted. I opened my eyes. My love sat close beside me in the shadow of the poplars. One hand held both my own, while with the other she arranged my pillows and stroked my aching head. The world dropped back into a tiny scale once more.

“You have had the pain again,” Marion murmured anxiously, “but it is better now. It is passing.” She kissed my cheek. “You must come in. …”

But I would not let her go. I held her to me with all the strength that was in me. “I had it, but it’s gone again. An awful darkness came with it,” I whispered in the little ear that was so close against my mouth. “I’ve been dreaming,” I told her, as memory dipped away, “dreaming of you and me—together somewhere—in old gardens, or forests—where the sun was—”

But she would not let me finish. I think, in any case, I could not have said more, for thought evaded me, and any language of coherent description was in the same instant beyond my power. Exhaustion came upon me, that vile, compelling nausea with it.

“The sun here is too strong for you, dear love,” I heard her saying, “and you must rest more. We have been doing too much these last few days. You must have more repose.” She rose to help me move indoors.

“I have been unconscious then?” I asked, in the feeble whisper that was all I could manage.

“For a little while. You slept, while I watched over you.”

“But I was away from you! Oh, how could you let me sleep, when our time together is so short?”

She soothed me instantly in the way she knew we both loved so. I clung to her until she released herself again.

“Not away from me,” she smiled, “for I was with you in your dreaming.”

“Of course, of course you were”; but already I knew not exactly why I said it, nor caught the deep meaning that struggled up into my words from such unfathomable distance.

“Come,” she added, with her sweet authority again, “we must go in now. Give me your arm, and I will send out for the cushions. Lean on me. I am going to put you back to bed.”

“But I shall sleep again,” I said petulantly, “and we shall be separated.”

“We shall dream together,” she replied, as she helped me slowly and painfully towards the old grey walls of the château.

II

Half an hour later I slept deeply, peacefully, upon my bed in the big stately chamber where the roses watched beside the latticed windows.

And to say I dreamed again is not correct, for it can only be expressed by saying that I saw and knew. The figures round the bed were actual, and in life. Nothing could be more real than the whisper of the doctor’s voice—that solemn, grave-faced man who was so tall—as he said, sternly yet brokenly, to someone: “You must say goodbye; and you had better say it now.” Nor could anything be more definite and sure, more charged with the actuality of living, than the figure of Marion, as she stooped over me to obey the terrible command. For I saw her face float down towards me like a star, and a shower of pale spring blossoms rained upon me with her hair. The perfume of old, old gardens rose about me as she slipped to her knees beside the bed and kissed my lips—so softly it was like the breath of wind from lake and orchard, and so lingeringly it was as though the blossoms lay upon my mouth and grew into flowers that she planted there.

“Goodbye, my love; be brave. It is only separation.”

“It is death,” I tried to say, but could only feebly stir my lips against her own.

I drew her breath of flowers into my mouth … and there came then the darkness which is final.

The voices grew louder. I heard a man struggling with an unfamiliar language. Turning restlessly, I opened my eyes—upon a little, stuffy room, with white walls whereon no pictures hung. It was very hot. A woman was standing beside the bed, and the bed was very short. I stretched, and my feet kicked against the boarding at the end.

“Yes, he is awake,” the woman said in French. “Will you come in? The doctor said you might see him when he woke. I think he’ll know you.” She spoke in French. I just knew enough to understand.

And of course I knew him. It was Haddon. I heard him thanking her for all her kindness, as he blundered in. His French, if anything, was worse than my own. I felt inclined to laugh. I did laugh.

“By Jove! old man, this is bad luck, isn’t it? You’ve had a narrow shave. This good lady telegraphed—”

“Have you got my ice-axe? Is it all right?” I asked. I remembered clearly the motor accident—everything.

“The ice-axe is right enough,” he laughed, looking cheerfully at the woman, “but what about yourself? Feel bad still? Any pain, I mean?”

“Oh, I feel all right,” I answered, searching for the pain of broken bones, but finding none. “What happened? I was stunned, I suppose?”

“Bit stunned, yes,” said Haddon. “You got a nasty knock on the head, it seems. The point of the axe ran into you, or something.”

“Was that all?”

He nodded. “But I’m afraid it’s knocked our climbing on the head. Shocking bad luck, isn’t it?”

“I telegraphed last night,” the kind woman was explaining.

“But I couldn’t get here till this morning,” Haddon said. “The telegram didn’t find me till midnight, you see.” And he turned to thank the woman in his voluble, dreadful French. She kept a little pension on the shores of the lake. It was the nearest house, and they had carried me in there and got the doctor to me all within the hour. It proved slight enough, apart from the shock. It was not even concussion. I had merely been stunned. Sleep had cured me, as it seemed.

“Jolly little place,” said Haddon, as he moved me that afternoon to Geneva, whence, after a few days’ rest, we went on into the Alps of Haute Savoie, “and lucky the old body was so kind and quick. Odd, wasn’t it?” He glanced at me.

Something in his voice betrayed he hid another thought. I saw nothing “odd” in it at all, only very tiresome.

“What’s its name?” I asked, taking a shot at a venture.

He hesitated a second. Haddon, the climber, was not skilled in the delicacies of tact.

“Don’t know its present name,” he answered, looking away from me across the lake, “but it stands on the site of an old château—destroyed a hundred years ago—the Château de Bellerive.”

And then I understood my old friend’s absurd confusion. For Bellerive chanced also to be the name of a married woman I knew in Scotland—at least, it was her maiden name, and she was of French extraction.

Wind

It is a curious reflection, though of course an obvious one, that wind in itself is-silent; and that only from the friction against objects set in its path comes the multiform music instantly associated with its name. The fact, too, that so potent a force should be both silent and invisible readily explains its common use as a simile, and a beautiful one, for Spirit. Like flame, that other exquisite simile of spirit, how clean it licks, how mysteriously it moves, how swiftly it penetrates ! And so subtly linked are they that the one almost seems to produce the other—the swift hot winds that beat about a conflagration; the tongues of fire that follow a fanning draught," the wind that blew the stars to flame !" True inspiration seems certainly born of this marriage of wind and fire. How singular-have you ever thought ?would be the impressions of a man to whom the motion of air, as wind, was unknown, when first he witnessed the phenomenon of a twenty-knot breeze. Imagine a people that knew not wind—

how they would tremble to see the tree-tops bend; to hear the roar, the whispers, the sweet singing of all Nature about them for the first time; to know the sounds and movements of the myriad objects that but for wind would be silent and motionless from one year's' end to another ! To me, it has always seemed that such such a revelation might be far more wonderful than the first torrent of light that beats upon the eyes of a man who has been blind…

And so one comes to a further suggestive reflection : that objects all possess their own particular sound or voice that the winds love to set free; their essential note—that specific set of vibrations lying buried in their form-of which, as some curious doctrines of the old magic assert, their forms, indeed, are the visible expression. In this region-pondering the rela- tion between sound and shape—the imagination may wander till it grows dizzy, for it leads very soon to the still more wonderful world where sound and colour spin their puzzling web, and the spiritual phenomena of music cry for further explanation. But, for the moment, let only the sound of wind be in our ears; for in wind, I think, there is a sweetness and a variety of music that no instruments invented by men have yet succeeded in approaching so far as sheer thrill and beauty are concerned.

Each lover of Nature knows, of course, the special voice of wind that most appeals to him the sighing of pines, the shouting of oaks, the murmur of grasses, the whirring over a bare hillside, or the whistling about the corners of the streets—the variety is endless; and there can be no great interest in obtruding one's own predilection. Only, to know this music thoroughly, to catch all the overtones and undertones that make it so wonderful, and to absorb its essential thrill and power, you must listen, not for minutes, but for hours. If you want to learn the secrets of the things themselves, betrayed in the varying response they give back to the winds that sweep or caress them, lie leisurely for hours at a time and—listen.

How, from the high desolation of mountain peaks it blows out-terror, yet from the sea of bearded grain calls with soft whispering sounds such as children use for their tales of mystery; from old buildings—the melancholy of all dead human passion, yet from the rigging of ships the abandon of wild and passionate adventure: wind, clapping its mighty hands among the flapping sails, or running with weary little feet among the ruined towers of broken habitations; sighing with long, gentle music over English lawns, or rushing, full of dreams, across vast prairies over-seas; kissing a garden into music, or blundering blind-eyed through dark London squares; racing with thoughts of ice down precipices and dropping, as through spaces of sleep, into little corners of oblivion in waste lands of loneliness and desolation, or sighing with almost human melody through the keyhole and down the farmhouse chimney.

From the curtained softness of the summer sky these viewless winds sift silently into the heart, to wake yearnings infinite. From some high attic window, perhaps, where you stand and watch, listen to that wind of sighs that rises, almost articulate with the pains and sorrows, the half-caught joys, too, from that crowded human world beneath the sea of roofs and tiles. Winds of desire, winds of hope, winds of fear and love. Ah! winds of all the spirit's life and moods . . . and, finally, the wind of Death! And wind down a wet and deserted London street, shouting its whistling song, its song of the triumphant desolation that has cleared the way for it of human obstructionhow it sings the music of magnificent poverty, of heavy luxury, and then of the loneliness bred by both! And you see some solitary figure battling forwards, and hear that curious whistling it makes over the dripping umbrella. . Ah! how that wind summons pictures of courage in isolation, and of singing in a wilderness ! “The wind bloweth where it listeth, and thou hearest the sound thereof, yet canst not tell whence it cometh nor whither it goeth for wind is, indeed, of the nature of spirit, and its music, crowded with suggestion, as sometimes, too, with memory and association, is, in the true sense, magical.

“Where is thy soul? Thou liest i' the wind and rain," says the poetess to the “ Beloved Dead”; and in another passage the sound of wind brings back for her the phantom face of the departed : " But who shall drive a a mournful face from the sad winds about my door ?" Shelley, more than any other, perhaps, loved wind and wind-voices, and has the most marvellous and subtle descriptions of it in his work. Though he so often speaks of the “ viewless wind," one cannot one cannot help thinking that in his imagination lay some mental picture of wind in the terms of sight. He saw the wind. For him it had colour as well as shape. He saw bright sylphs-spirits of air-which star the winds with points of coloured light, they rain through them," and enchanted shapes of wandering mist ” that for his inner vision were" snow-white and swift as wind nursed among lilies near a brimming stream." And, alone among poets so far as I know, he had that delightful conception of solid, smooth surfaces of wind upon which it is possible to run and dance and sleep. His verse is alive with spirits “trampling the wind"; trampling the slant winds on high with goldensandalled feet"; or climbing the hills of wind that run up into the highest peaks of heaven. The “ Witch of Atlas " not only rode " singing as through the shoreless air," but also“ ran upon the platforms of the wind, and laughed to hear the fireballs roar behind." And it is the Chorus in Prometheus Unbound that so exquisitely weaves the dance on the floor of the breeze."

But for less gifted mortals there are certain effects of wind that seem to me to approach uncommonly close to actual sight, or at least to a point where one may imagine what wind ought to look like. Watch the gusts of a northwest wind as they fall in rapid succession upon a standing field of high barley, beating the surface into long curved shadows that bring to mind Shelley's “kindling within the strings of the waved air, Æolian modulations." One can see the velvet touch of those soft, vast paws, and the immense stretch of the invisible footsteps that press the long stalks down and as suddenly sweep away and set them free again. And with the changing angle of the myriad yellow heads the colour also changes, till gradually there swims upon the mind the impression of some huge and shadowy image that flies above the field-some personal deity of wind, some djin of air. One almost sees the spirit of the wind....

It is fascinating, too, to stand opposite a slope of wooded mountains, near enough to distinguish the individual swing of each separate tree, yet far enough to note how the forest as a whole blows all one way—the way of the wind. Also-to hear the chord of sound as a whole, yet mark the different notes that pour out of the various trees composing it. In some such wayone wonders, perhaps the Spirit of God moves over the surface of men's minds, each swinging apparently its own individual way, yet when seen in proper perspective, all moving the one way - to Him. And the voices of all these separate little stray winds—who shall describe them ? Creep with me now out of the house among these Jura vineyards, and come up into the pine forests that encircle the village. Put your ear against that bosom of the soft dark woods where the wind is born and listen ! Find the words if you can—!

Wireless Confusion

“Good night, Uncle,” whispered the child, as she climbed on to his knee and gave him a resounding kiss. “It’s time for me to disappop into bed—at least, so mother says.”

“Disappop, then,” he replied, returning her kiss, “although I doubt. …”

He hesitated. He remembered the word was her father’s invention, descriptive of the way rabbits pop into their holes and disappear, and the way good children should leave the room the instant bedtime was announced. The father—his twin brother—seemed to enter the room and stand beside them. “Then give me another kiss, and disappop!” he said quickly. The child obeyed the first part of his injunction, but had not obeyed the second when the queer thing happened. She had not left his knee; he was still holding her at the full stretch of both arms; he was staring into her laughing eyes, when she suddenly went far away into an extraordinary distance. She retired. Minute, tiny, but still in perfect proportion and clear as before, she was withdrawn in space till she was small as a doll. He saw his own hands holding her, and they too were minute. Down this long corridor of space, as it were, he saw her diminutive figure.

“Uncle!” she cried, yet her voice was loud as before, “but what a funny face! You’re pretending you’ve seen a ghost”—and she was gone from his knee and from the room, the door closing quietly behind her. He saw her cross the floor, a tiny figure. Then, just as she reached the door, she became of normal size again, as if she crossed a line.

He felt dizzy. The loud voice close to his ear issuing from a diminutive figure half a mile away had a distressing effect upon him. He knew a curious qualm as he sat there in the dark. He heard the wind walking round the house, trying the doors and windows. He was troubled by a memory he could not seize.

Yet the emotion instantly resolved itself into one of personal anxiety: something had gone wrong with his eyes. Sight, his most precious possession as an artist, was of course affected. He was conscious of a little trembling in him, as he at once began trying his sight at various objects—his hands, the high ceiling, the trees dim in the twilight on the lawn outside. He opened a book and read half a dozen lines, at changing distances; finally he stared carefully at the second hand of his watch. “Right as a trivet!” he exclaimed aloud. He emitted a long sigh; he was immensely relieved. “Nothing wrong with my eyes.”

He thought about the actual occurrence a great deal—he felt as puzzled as any other normal person must have felt. While he held the child actually in his arms, gripping her with both hands, he had seen her suddenly half a mile away. “Half a mile!” he repeated under his breath, “why it was even more, it was easily a mile.” It had been exactly as though he suddenly looked at her down the wrong end of a powerful telescope. It had really happened; he could not explain it; there was no more to be said.

This was the first time it happened to him.

At the theatre, a week later, when the phenomenon was repeated, the stage he was watching fixedly at the moment went far away, as though he saw it from a long way off. The distance, so far as he could judge, was the same as before, about a mile. It was an Eastern scene, realistically costumed and produced, that without an instant’s warning withdrew. The entire stage went with it, although he did not actually see it go. He did not see movement, that is. It was suddenly remote, while yet the actors’ voices, the orchestra, the general hubbub retained their normal volume. He experienced again the distressing dizziness; he closed his eyes, covering them with his hand, then rubbing the eyeballs slightly; and when he looked up the next minute, the world was as it should be, as it had been, at any rate. Unwilling to experience a repetition of the thing in a public place, however, and fortunately being alone, he left the theatre at the end of the act.

Twice this happened to him, once with an individual, his brother’s child, and once with a landscape, an Eastern stage scene. Both occurrences were within the week, during which time he had been considering a visit to the oculist, though without putting his decision into execution. He was the kind of man that dreaded doctors, dentists, oculists, always postponing, always finding reasons for delay. He found reasons now, the chief among them being an unwelcome one—that it was perhaps a brain specialist, rather than an oculist, he ought to consult. This particular notion hung unpleasantly about his mind, when, the day after the theatre visit, the thing recurred, but with a startling difference.

While idly watching a bluebottle fly that climbed the windowpane with remorseless industry, only to slip down again at the very instant when escape into the open air was within its reach, the fly grew abruptly into gigantic proportions, became blurred and indistinct as it did so, covered the entire pane with its furry, dark, ugly mass, and frightened him so that he stepped back with a cry and nearly lost his balance altogether. He collapsed into a chair. He listened with closed eyes. The metallic buzzing was audible, a small, exasperating sound, ordinarily unable to stir any emotion beyond a mild annoyance. Yet it was terrible; that so huge an insect should make so faint a sound seemed to him terrible.

At length he cautiously opened his eyes. The fly was of normal size once more. He hastily flicked it out of the window.

An hour later he was talking with the famous oculist in Harley Street … about the advisability of starting reading-glasses. He found it difficult to relate the rest. A curious shyness restrained him.

“Your optic nerves might belong to a man of twenty,” was the verdict. “Both are perfect. But at your age it is wise to save the sight as much as possible. There is a slight astigmatism. …” And a prescription for the glasses was written out. It was only when paying the fee, and as a means of drawing attention from the awkward moment, that his story found expression. It seemed to come out in spite of himself. He made light of it even then, telling it without conviction. It seemed foolish suddenly as he told it. “How very odd,” observed the oculist vaguely, “dear me, yes, curious indeed. But that’s nothing. H’m, h’m!” Either it was no concern of his, or he deemed it negligible. … His only other confidant was a friend of psychological tendencies who was interested and eager to explain. It is on the instant plausible explanation of anything and everything that the reputation of such folk depends; this one was true to type: “A spontaneous invention, my dear fellow—a pictorial rendering of your thought. You are a painter, aren’t you? Well, this is merely a rendering in picture-form of”—he paused for effect, the other hung upon his words—“of the odd expression ‘disappop.’ ”

“Ah!” exclaimed the painter.

“You see everything pictorially, of course, don’t you?”

“Yes—as a rule.”

“There you have it. Your painter’s psychology saw the child ‘disappopping.’ That’s all.”

“And the fly?” but the fly was easily explained, since it was merely the process reversed. “Once a process has established itself in your mind, you see, it may act in either direction. When a madman says ‘I’m afraid Smith will do me an injury,’ it means, ‘I will do an injury to Smith,’ ” And he repeated with finality, “That’s it.”

The explanations were not very satisfactory, the illustration even tactless, but then the problem had not been stated quite fully. Neither to the oculist nor to the other had all the facts been given. The same shyness had been a restraining influence in both cases; a detail had been omitted, and this detail was that he connected the occurrences somehow with his brother whom the war had taken.

The phenomenon made one more appearance—the last—before its character, its field of action rather, altered. He was reading a book when the print became now large, now small; it blurred, grew remote and tiny, then so huge that a single word, a letter even, filled the whole page. He felt as if someone were playing optical tricks with the mechanism of his eyes, trying first one, then another focus.

More curious still, the meaning of the words themselves became uncertain; he did not understand them any more; the sentences lost their meaning, as though he read a strange language, or a language little known. The flash came then—someone was using his eyes—someone else was looking through them.

No, it was not his brother. The idea was preposterous in any case. Yet he shivered again, as when he heard the walking wind, for an uncanny conviction came over him that it was someone who did not understand eyes but was manipulating their mechanism experimentally. With the conviction came also this: that, while not his brother, it was someone connected with his brother.

Here, moreover, was an explanation of sorts, for if the supernatural existed—he had never troubled his head about it—he could accept this odd business as a manifestation, and leave it at that. He did so, and his mind was eased. This was his attitude: “The supernatural may exist. Why not? We cannot know. But we can watch.” His eyes and brain, at any rate, were proved in good condition.

He watched. No change of focus, no magnifying or diminishing, came again. For some weeks he noticed nothing unusual of any kind, except that his mind often filled now with Eastern pictures. Their sudden irruption caught his attention, but no more than that; they were sometimes blurred and sometimes vivid; he had never been in the East; he attributed them to his constant thinking of his brother, missing in Mesopotamia these six months. Photographs in magazines and newspapers explained the rest. Yet the persistence of the pictures puzzled him: tents beneath hot cloudless skies, palms, a stretch of desert, dry watercourses, camels, a mosque, a minaret—typical snatches of this kind flashed into his mind with a sense of faint familiarity often. He knew, again, the return of a fugitive memory he could not seize. … He kept a note of the dates, all of them subsequent to the day he read his brother’s fate in the official Roll of Honour: “Believed missing; now killed.” Only when the original phenomenon returned, but in its altered form, did he stop the practice. The change then affected his life too fundamentally to trouble about mere dates and pictures.

For the phenomenon, shifting its field of action, abruptly became mental, and the singular change of focus took place now in his mind. Events magnified or contracted themselves out of all relation with their intrinsic values, sense of proportion went hopelessly astray. Love, hate and fear experienced sudden intensification, or abrupt dwindling into nothing; the familiar everyday emotions, commonplace daily acts, suffered exaggerated enlargement, or reduction into insignificance, that threatened the stability of his personality. Fortunately, as stated, they were of brief duration; to examine them in detail were to touch the painful absurdities of incipient mania almost; that a lost collar stud could block his exasperated mind for hours, filling an entire day with emotion, while a deep affection of long standing could ebb towards complete collapse suddenly without apparent cause … !

It was the unexpected suddenness of Turkey’s spectacular defeat that closed the painful symptoms. The Armistice saw them go. He knew a quick relief he was unable to explain. The telegram that his brother was alive and safe came after his recovery of mental balance. It was a shock. But the phenomena had ceased before the shock.

It was in the light of his brother’s story that he reviewed the puzzling phenomena described. The story was not more curious than many another, perhaps, yet the details were queer enough. That a wounded Turk to whom he gave water should have remembered gratitude was likely enough, for all travellers know that these men are kindly gentlemen at times; but that this Mohammedan peasant should have been later a member of a prisoner’s escort and have provided the means of escape and concealment—weeks in a dry watercourse and months in a hut outside the town—seemed an incredible stroke of good fortune. “He brought me food and water three times a week. I had no money to give him, so I gave him my Zeiss glasses. I taught him a bit of English too. But he liked the glasses best. He was never tired of playing with ’em—making big and little, as he called it. He learned precious little English. …”

“My pair, weren’t they?” interrupted his brother. “My old climbing glasses.”

“Your present to me when I went out, yes. So really you helped me to save my life. I told the old Turk that. I was always thinking about you.”

“And the Turk?”

“No doubt. … Through my mind, that is. At any rate, he asked a lot of questions about you. I showed him your photo. He died, poor chap—at least they told me so. Probably they shot him.”

With the Russian Pilgrims to Jerusalem

With the Russian Pilgrims to Jerusalem by Stephen Graham, Reviewed by Algernon Blackwood

To have seen the Holy Land as Stephen Graham saw it is a privilege many might desire, but few deserve. He saw it as a genuine pilgrim himself, one among the seven thousand others from the cold interior of Russia; and, in order to do so, he endured no little hardship and privation by the way. Tramps are plentiful to-day, overdone, in fact ; tramping is almost as fashionable a pose as caravanning. But pilgrims are rare. A pilgrim may take as little luggage as a tramp, but where the tramp is a mere wanderer, listless as the wind, the pilgrim has a definite goal, usually difficult of attainment. He has, moreover, faith, and the city he seeks lies hid in that vastest and most puzzling of all strange lands—the heart. These seven thousand Russian peasants, journeying to Jerusalem, months and months on foot, journeyed at the same time to the goal of all their lives, the New Jerusalem. The account is full of a grand and tender pathos ; told in few words, with a simplicity almost of Bible language, it is moving and beautiful. Those obvious stage effects that seduce most writers on the Holy Land are con- temptuously ignored ; except for a few vivid touches the author himself hardly appears at all; one sees only the crowd of aged Pilgrims (there are no young among them), confusion in their minds but ecstasy in their hearts, scornful of pain, discomfort, even of death itself, moving in a body to that Holy City where Christ was crucified and buried, and where He rose again. That, having seen, they may go home to die. Their pilgrimage s Over. It is a fortunate thing that the first man to describe this unique and remarkable pilgrimage should be one who could have written “A Tramp’s Sketches” ’ and ‘A Vagabond in the Caucasus,” both of them revealing a type of mind and heart Not too common in the army of writing folk to-day. Only a man of simple, understanding heart, yet with the faith and vision of a poet, could do justice to such a theme. ‘‘ The adventure of which I tell,” ’ he says in his preface, ‘‘ was unique and splendid, a thing of a lifetime. The journey of the Russian peasants to Jerusalem has never been described before in any language, not even in Russian. Yet it is the most significant thing in the Russian life of to-day. In the story lies a great national epic.” And on laying down the story at its close the reader feels these latter words are justified. ‘ There is, unfortunately, no litera- ture of the pilgrimage,” he says elsewhere (page 215). ‘I find nothing that is historically of the slightest value. No one of any literary ability seems to have ever journeyed with the pilgrims and brought a story home. It is strange that an immemorial national pilgrimage should have remained unsung. It shows how divorced is the interest of the Russian cultured Class from that which is essentially Russian. … Certainly, for a great Russian writer there is the outward form and visible expression of greatness lying potentially in the pilgrimage. There is the possibility of a great national epic that would make Europe ring. Of course, it needs a Russian to write it—one can write a national epic only for one’s own nation.”

This, of course, is true. But herein lies the touch of genius that lifts this remarkable book above others of its ilk, namely, that it is written from the point of view of an insider, as though one of the peasants themselves had told it to his family on getting home again. No mere observant outsider travelling with the band could have done this. The insight, sympathy and intimate understanding of the peasant mind v/s a vis to these realised splendours of his life-long faith and worship are no common gift.

To give a résumé of this great pilgrimage within the space of a brief notice is hardly possible. ‘‘ The pilgrimage is not so much to the Holy Land or to Jerusalem as to the sacred stones.” It is a promise the peasant gives to his God. ‘ The peasants feel that when they have been to Jerusalem the serious occupa- tions of their life are all ended. They take their death-sh:ouds to Jordan and, wearing them, bathe in the sacred river … They spend a night in the sepulchre of Christ, and Teceivirys the Sacred Fire (chemically provided by the mercenary monk: } extinguish it with caps that they will wear in their coffins. They mostly hope to die in the Holy Land, preferably near the Dead Sea, whee the Last Judgment will take place. If they must retum to their native village in Russia, it will be to put their affairs in order and await death.” The obvious chicanery and fraud practised on them everywhere has no effect upon them, whether they buy an actual fragment of the Virgin’s gown or touch a plank that Jesus himself planed, for their passion- ate belief sublimates all tawdry hum- bug into beauty, and these details are to them but external symbols of a faith in their hearts which is inextin- guishable. Some of them went to see the oak tree under which Abra- ham enter- tained three angels un- awares. “A tremendous oak,” said one of them. “To think that it has lived all these thousands of years, and that my unworthy’ eyes should survive to see it!” For guide-books they use their Bibles, which they bring out with them. Some of them have tramped four thousand miles, taking years to reach the seaport where they may embark. From every part of the great Empire they come; and it is no artificia) movement organised by priests or clergy. They come because the mandate is in their hearts. For months before the journey begins they set aside crusts of bread to carry with them, and these crusts, yellow, green and mouldy, form the chief sustenance of the larger portion on the way. The procession, as it goes from Jerusalem to Nazareth, is over a mile in length, and though mules are provided by the Russian Palestine Society for those who may succumb, the majority prefer to suffer pain and misery, moving at the rate of half a mile an hour beneath the blistering sun rather than ride—since Christ himself walked and bore a burden too. All bring money, some more, some less, and of this, what does not go to the greedy monks for the saying of prayers goes into the pockets of the shopmen who sell sacred articles of every sort and description at exorbitant prices. A great sale is done, especially in ready-made letters (since the peasants can neither read nor write) written with high- sounding phrases and suitable to send to any friend in Russia, full, moreover, of ‘‘ pious opinions all written with superb flourishes of caligraphy in gold-coloured ink.”

It is more edifying, as well as better worth while, however, to dwell upon the charity and spirit of kindliness that animated the entire army of seven thousand simple peasants, and to read how they shared their food and money and clothing with each other, tended each other in sickness, prayed and sang and laughed together like a lot of children journeying to fairyland. There is something inspiring in the record, superstitious though the underlying faith may seem to most. “ With the Russian Pilgrims to Jerusalem ” ’ is a poem, and a poem to read again and again with deep enjoyment. :

It is not fair, I feel, to steal fragments from the text, or one would like to give the account of the effect of ‘‘ Jerusalem attained” upon these pilgrims, their ecstasies in the Holy Sepulchre, in the Garden of Gethsemane, at Nazareth and Bethleliem, and, above all, on Easter Morning. The scene in the Church of the Holy Sepulchre when the Sacred Fire blazes from the wall, and the pilgrims light lamps and candles they mean to carry back alight to their villages, thousands of miles away, is movingly described. The “ Bringing out of the Holy Shroud,” and, indeed, the entire Easter Festival will live vividly in the reader’s memory as a picture of solemn and pathetic beauty. This, however, and the details of the tremen- dous journey, of the appalling voyage by sea from Constantinople to Jaffa, of the sleeping places, mysterious bed-fellows, as well as the enchanting accounts of individual Pilgrims, must all be read where they belong, in the atmosphere and setting of the book and in the author’s own simple, thrilling language The farewell address to the pilgrims by the Archimandnte is given in the final chapter. It is a singular and characteristic utterance. He gives thanks to God that all have seen the HoLy Land, “the wish of every Orthodox Russian Christian.” Many had died on the Way; he holds then: fortunate too. “We have been in Bethlehem where the Child was born, and in Nazareth where He lived thiny years. We have washed Our sinful bodies in the holy Jordan gtreams where He was baptised, have climbed Tabor where He was transfigured, and walked in Jerusalem where He was crucified, buried, and raised from death. The names of the places in. which we have prayed have made our very hearts tremble. .- . . We have followed - in the footsteps of Jesus Christ from Bethlehem to Golgotha. … When we go back to Russia we must never forget cur visions.” And then, with worldly wisdom, he adds, finally: “We have seen much that is evil in the Holy Land. Do net let us, therefore, take home tales of evil things seen and heard there. Forget that which was not good.” One feels, te. from the general tenour and character of the pilgnms, that it is only the good they will take home to their remote and frozen villages. ‘‘ For all these different hearts,” as Mr. Graham says, “ felt each its own particular joy. Each peasant, thowl in sheepskins, throbbed and glowed in the temple. Not on ‘he, but the village for which he stood, and the family for whic: ihe stood, had reached Jerusalem … and the peasat! entering Jerusalem with his prayers brought all these win him. A mighty chorus went up to God of the voices of the human heart, a music not heard by the ear. It was the voice oF a great nation in the presence of God.”

You May Telephone from Here

She sent the servant to bed at half-past ten, and sat up in the flat alone. “I’ll let my cousin in,” she explained; and “she may be rather late.” She read, knitted, began a letter, poked the fire, and examined here husband’s photographs on the mantelpiece; but most of the time she looked about her nervously, sometimes going to the door to listen, sometimes lifting the corner of the blind to look out upon the lights of North Kensington struggling with the blackness. The fog was thicker than ever. A fumble of traffic feeling its way floated up to her from below.

But at last the doorbell rang sharply, and she ran to let the cousin who had promised to spend the two nights wither during their husband’s absence in Paris. They kissed. Both began talking at once.

“I thought you were never coming, Sybil—!”

“The play was out late—and the fog’s bad. I sent on my box this afternoon on purpose.”

“It came safely; and your room’s quite ready. I do hope you’ll manage all right without a maid. Oh, I’m so glad you’ve come, though!”

“Foolish little country mouse!”

“Oh, it’s not that so much, though I admit that London still terrifies me at night rather; but you know this is the first time he’s been away—and I suppose—”

“I know , dear; I understand perfectly.” The cousin was brisk and cheerful. “You feel lonely, of course.” They kissed again. “Just unhook me, will you?” she added, “and I’ll get into my dressing-gown, and then we’ll be cosy over the fire.”

“I saw him off at Victoria at 8:45,” said the little wife when the operation was over.

“Newhaven and Dieppe?”

“Yes. He gets to Paris at seven in the morning. He promised to telephone the first thing.”

“You expensive little monkey!”

“Why?”

“It’s ten shillings for three minutes, or something like that, and if you go to the G.P.O or the Mansion House or some such place, I believe.”

“But, I thought it was the usual long-distance thing direct here to to the flat. He never told me all that.”

“Probably you didn’t give him the chance!”

They laughed, and went on chatting, with feet on the fender and skirts tucked up. The cousin lit her second cigarette. It was after midnight.

“I’m afraid I’m not the least bit sleepy,” said the wife apologetically.

“Nor am I, dear. For once the play excited me.” She began to describe it vigorously. Halfway through the recital the telephone sounded in the hall. It tinkled faintly, but gave no proper ring.

The other started. “There it is again! It’s always doing that—ever since Harry put it in a week ago. I don’t quite like it.” She spoke in a hushed voice.

Her cousin looked at her curiously. “Oh, you mustn’t mind that,” she laughed with a reassuring manner. “It’s a little way they have when the line gets out of order. You’re not used to playing the telephone game yet. You should call up the Exchange and complain. Always complain, you know, in this world if you want—”

“There it goes again,” interrupted her friend nervously. “Oh I do wish it would stop. It’s like someone standing out there in the hall and trying to talk—”

The cousin jumped up. They went into the hall together, and the experienced one briskly rang up the Exchange and asked if there was anybody trying to “get through.” With a fine indignation she complained that no one in the flat could sleep for the noise. After a brief conversation she turned, receiver in hand, to her companion.

“The operator says he’s very sorry, but your line’s a bit troublesome tonight for some reason. Got mixed or something. he can’t understand it. Advises you to leave the receiver unhooked till morning. Then it can’t possibly ring, you see!”

They left the receiver swinging, and went back to the fire.

“I’m sorry I’m such a timid donkey,” the wife said, laughing a little; “but I’m not used to it yet. There was no telephone at the farm, you know.” She turned with a sudden start, as thought she heard the bell again. “And tonight,” she added with a lower voice, thought with an obvious effort at self-control, “for some reason or other I feel uncomfortable, rather—excited, queer, I think.”

“How? Queer?”

“I don’t know exactly; almost as if there was someone else in the flat—someone besides ourselves and the servant, I mean.”

The cousin moved abruptly. She switched on the electric lights in the wall beside her.

“Yes; but it’s only imagination, really,” she said with decision. “It’s natural enough. It’s the fog and the strangeness of London after the loneliness of your farm-life, and your husband being away and—and all that. Once you analyse, these queer feelings they always go—”

“Hark!” exclaimed the wife under her breath. “Wasn’t that a step in the passage?” She sat bolt upright. They listened a moment. The night was utterly still about them.

“Rubbish!” cried the cousin loudly. “It was my foot knocking the fender; like this—look!” She repeated the sound vigorously.

“I do believe it was,” the other said, only half convinced. “But it is queer. You know I feel exactly as though someone had come into the flat—quite recently, since you came, I mean—just before that tinkling began, in fact.”

“Come, come,” laughed the cousin, “you’ll give us both the jumps. At one o’clock in the morning it’s easy to imagine anything. You’ll be hearing elephants in the stairs next!” She looked sharply about her. “Let’s brew our chocolate and get to bed,” she added. “We shall sleep like tops.”

“One o’clock already!” Then Harry’s halfway across by new,” said the wife smiling at her friend’s language. “But I’m so glad, oh, so glad, you’re here,” she added; “and I think it’s most awfully sweet of you to give up a comfy big house …” They kissed again and laughed. Soon afterwards, having scalded their throats with hot chocolate, they went to bed.

It simply can’t ring now!” remarked the cousin triumphantly as they passed the receiver dangling in midair.

“That’s a relief,” her friend said. “I feel less nervous. Really, I’m too ashamed of myself for anything.”

“Fog’s clearing, too,” Sybil added, peering for a moment through the narrow window by the front door.

An hour later the little flat was still as the grave. No sound of traffic was heard. Even the tinkling of the telephone seemed a whole twenty-four hours away, when suddenly—it began again: first with little soft tentative noises, very faint, troubled, hurried, buried louder and louder, with sharp jerks—finally with a challenging and alarming peal. And the wife, who had kept her door open, without pretence of sleep, heard it from the very beginning. In a moment she found herself in the passage, and Sybil, wakened by her cry, was at her heels. They turned up the lights and stood facing one another. The hall smelt—as things only smell at night—cold, must …

“What’s the matter? You frightened me. I heard you scream—!”

“The telephone’s ringin again—violently,” the wife whispered, pale to the lips. “Don’t you hear it? This time there’s someone there—really!”

The cousin stared blankly at her. The laugh choked in her throat. “I hear nothing,” she said defiantly, yet without confidence in her voice. “Besides, the thing’s still disconnected. It can’t ring—look!” She pointed at the hanging receiver motionless against the wall. “You’re white as a ghost, though,” she added, coming quickly forward. Her friend moved suddenly to the instrument and picked up the receiver. “It’s someone for me,” she said, with terror in her eyes. “It’s someone who want to talk to me! Oh, hard! hard how it rings!” Her voice shook. She placed the little disc to her ear and waited while her friend stood by and stared in amazement, uncertain what to do. She had heard not ringing!

“You, Harry!” whispered the wife into the telephone, with brief intervals of silence for the replies. “You! But how in the world so soon!—Yes, I can just hear you, but very faintly. Miles and miles away your voice sounds—What?”—A wonderful journey? And sooner than you expected!Not in Paris? Where, then?—Oh! my darling boy—No, I don’t quite hear; I can’t catch it—I don’t understand … The pain of the sea is nothing—is what? … You know nothing of what …”

The cousin came boldly up. She took her arm. “But, child, there’s no one there, bless you! You’re dreaming—you’re in fever or something—”

“Hush! For God’s sake, hush!” She held up a hand. In her face and eyes was an expression indescribably—fear, love, bewilderment. Her body swayed a little, leaning against the wall. “Hush! I hear him still; but, oh! miles and miles away—He ways—he’s been trying for hours to find me. First he tried my brain direct, and then—then—oh! he says he may not get back again to me—only he can’t understand, can’t explain why—the cold, the awful cold, keeps his lips from—Oh!”

She screamed aloud as she flung the receiver down and dropped in a heap upon the floor. “I don’t understand—it’s death, death!” …

And the collision in the Channel that night, as they learned in due course occurred a few minutes after one o’clock; while Harry himself, who remained unconscious for several hours after the boat picked him up, could only remember that his last desire as the wave caught him was an intense wish to communicate with his wife and tell her what had happened … The next thing he knew was opening his eyes in a Dieppe hotel.

And the other curious detail was furnished by the man who came to repair the telephone next day. At the Exchange, he declared, the wire, from midnight till near three in the morning, had emitted sparks and flashes of light no one had been able to account for in any usual manner.

“Queer!” said the main to himself, after tinkering and tapping for ten minutes, “but there’s nothing wrong with it at this end. It’s the subscriber, most likely. It usually is!”

Algernon Blackwood on Fiction Writing

Questions and replies excepted from Fiction Writers on Fiction Writing by Arthur Sullivant Hoffman (1923).

What is the genesis of a story with you—does it grow from an incident, a character, a trait of character, a situation, setting, a title, or what? That is, what do you mean by an idea for a story?

The genesis of a story with me is invariably—an emotion, caused in my particular case by something in nature rather than in human nature: a scrap of color in the sky, a flower, a sound of wind or water; briefly, an emotion produced by beauty.

Do you map it out in advance, or do you—start with, say, a character or situation, and let the story tell itself as you write? Do you write it in pieces to be joined together, or straightaway as a whole? Is the ending clearly in mind when you begin? To what extent do you revise?

An emotion produces its own setting, usually bringing with it a character who shall interpret it. The emotion dramatizes itself. The end alone is clearly in my mind. I never begin to write until this is so. Then I write fragments, scenes, fragments of the psychology, fitting them in later. Occasionally, however, when the emotion is strong, the story writes itself straight away. Revision is endless. Often the story, when finished, is put aside and forgotten. The revision that comes weeks later, on reading over the tale as though it had been written by someone else, is the most helpful of all.

When you read a story to what extent does your imagination reproduce the story-world of the author—do you actually see in your imagination all the characters, action and setting just as if you were looking at an actual scene? Do you actually hear all sounds described, mentioned and inferred, just as if they were real sounds? Do you taste the flavors in a story, so really that your mouth literally waters to a pleasant one? How real does your imagination make the smells in a story you read? Does your imagination reproduce the sense of touch—of rough or smooth contact, hard or gentle impact or pressure, etc.? Does your imagination make you feel actual physical pain corresponding, though in a slighter degree, to pain presented in a story? Of course you get an intelligent idea from any such mention, but in which of the above cases does your imagination produce the same results on your senses as do the actual stimuli themselves?

If you can really “see things with your eyes shut,” what limitations? Are the pictures you see colored or more in black and white? Are details distinct or blurred?

If you studied solid geometry, did it give you more trouble than other mathematics?

Is your response limited to the exact degree to which the author describes and makes vivid, or will the mere concept set you to reproducing just as vividly?

Do you have stock pictures for, say, a village church or a cowboy, or does each case produce its individual vision?

Is there any difference in behavior of your imagination when you are reading stories and when writing them?

Have you ever considered these matters as “tools of your trade”? If so, to what extent and how do you use them?

The visualization of a story I read depends entirely on its degree of actuality according to the evocative power of the writer. I prefer a suggestion that enables me to form my own pictures of scenes and characters described, rather than to have these formed for me in detail by the author. A description of house or room or garden I invariably skip. With his first vital adjective the scene flashes into my mind. His subsequent detail bores me.

When you write do you center your mind on the story itself or do you constantly have your readers in mind? In revising?

I never give the reader a single thought. To some imaginary reader, sitting at a desk inside my own mind, I tell my story. It is written to express—to relieve—an emotion in my own being. It is never written to please other readers or any imaginable public.

Have you had a classroom or correspondence course on writing fiction? Books on it? To what extent did this help in the elementary stages? Beyond the elementary stages?

No. I began writing at the age of thirty-six because I could not keep it back. I preferred an evening thus engaged to any pleasure, social, theatre, music or anything else. After a day of hard, uncongenial business, the imaginative release on paper was my real recreation.

How much of your craft have you learned from reading current authors? The classics?

None. I read little fiction. As a boy I missed the classics, and have only made up a little of this leeway since. I never read a story without feeling how completely otherwise my own treatment of his idea would have been—probably, that is, how much better his treatment is than mine.

What is your general feeling on the value of technique?

I have never consciously studied technique. Up to a point technique must be instinctive. But it can be overstressed. It can overlay an idea, especially a thin idea. Its value, of course, can not be over estimated. It is essential. But no textbook has ever helped me much.

What is most interesting and important to you in your writing—plot, structure, style, material, setting, character, color, etc.

Material, style, setting, character, color.

What are two or three of the most valuable suggestions you could give to a beginner? To a practised writer?

To a beginner—don’t write unless you simply can not keep it back. Write to please yourself. Never think of a public. Reduce your first attempts to the briefest possible length. See in how few words you can make your idea or plot intelligible. To a practised writer—feel dissatisfied with everything completed, put it aside and forget it entirely, then read it over months later—and revise.

What is the elemental hold of fiction on the human mind?

I do not know.

Do you prefer writing in the first person or the third? Why?

Third person. The use of the first person tends to remind a writer of himself, whereas fiction should mean an escape from one’s tiresome self—a projection into others.

Do you lose ideas because your imagination travels faster than your means of recording? Which affords least check pencil, typewriter or stenographer?

Imagination invariably travels faster than power of recording it. I use shorthand to jot down bits that flash ahead of the words I am actually typing at the moment. These flashes otherwise prove irrecoverable. With a stenographer beside me I could not think of a single sentence. I compose straight on to my own machine.